<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Judges judged out of their own mouthes or the question resolved by Magna charta, &amp;c. Who have been Englands enemies, kings seducers, and peoples destroyers, from Hen. 3. to Hen. 8. and before and since. Stated by Sr. Edvvard Coke, Knt. late L. Chief Justice of England. Expostulated, and put to the vote of the people, by J. Jones, Gent. Whereunto is added eight observable points of law, executable by justices of peace.</title>
            <author>Jones, J., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80048</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1414_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13507</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859485</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859485</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80048)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 182:E1414[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Judges judged out of their own mouthes or the question resolved by Magna charta, &amp;c. Who have been Englands enemies, kings seducers, and peoples destroyers, from Hen. 3. to Hen. 8. and before and since. Stated by Sr. Edvvard Coke, Knt. late L. Chief Justice of England. Expostulated, and put to the vote of the people, by J. Jones, Gent. Whereunto is added eight observable points of law, executable by justices of peace.</title>
                  <author>Jones, J., Gent.</author>
                  <author>Coke, Edward, Sir, 1552-1634.</author>
                  <author>England. Magna Charta.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 96, 99-117, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Bently, and are to be sold by E. Dod, and N. Ekins, at the Gun in Ivy-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCL. [1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Extracts of English statutes, with corresponding extracts of commentaries by Coke. Consists chiefly of commentary by Jones.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 6.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:111570:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:111570:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>JUDGES JUDGED out of their own mouthes. OR The QUESTION Reſolved by <hi>MAGNA CHARTA,</hi> &amp;c. Who have been <hi>Englands</hi> Enemies, <hi>Kings</hi> Seducers, and <hi>Peoples</hi> Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, from <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. to <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and before and ſince.</p>
                  <p>Stated by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. EDVVARD COKE, Kn<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. late L. Chief Juſtice of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Expoſtulated, and put to the Vote of the People, by <hi>J. JONES,</hi> Gent.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto is added <hi>Eight Obſervable Points of Law,</hi> Executable by Juſtices of Peace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abuſum ego, non uſum forenſem damne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Ex legibus illis quae non in tempus aliquod, ſea perpetuâ utilitatis cauſâ in aeternum latae ſunt, null: abrogari debet, niſi quam aut u ſus ceärguit, aut ſtatus aliquis Reipublica inutilem fecit.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Tit. Liv. lib. 4. dec. 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Bently,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>E. Dod,</hi> and <hi>N. Ekins,</hi> at the Gun in Ivy-Lane. MDCL.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:111570:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:111570:2"/>
                  <head>To the Right HONOURABLE, HONOURABLE; Right WORSHIPFULL, And Well-beloved, the COMMONS, and PEOPLE of <hi>England</hi> Univerſally.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe <hi>Magna Char.</hi> Printed in Engliſh, <hi>An. 1564.</hi> and bound up with other Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes at large (too Volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and coſtly for the generality to read, or buy) doth yield leſs profit than hath been long neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; I have preſumed at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſome, to Dedicate this Treatiſe to you all, as it concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:111570:3"/>the good of all that be, or would be good, &amp; the hurt of none that have left any unhurt: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you ſhall find ſo many Chap. of <hi>Mag. Char. Confir. Char. Art. ſuper Char.</hi> and other Statutes at large, corroborating the ſame; and the L. C. Expoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, with ſome Expoſtulations, and Queres of mine own, as I thought requiſite, or convenient for theſe times. The reſt of the <hi>Charter,</hi> concerning the Church, (yet unſetled) or the Kings Tenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, (otherways diſpoſed of) I have omitted as uſeleſs; deſiring that thus much may prove uſeful to all undertakers of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well Martial, as Civil.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Whoſe Servant (to my power) I ſhall ever be, and continue with due faithfulneſs, and humility.</hi> Jo. Jones.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111570:3"/>
                  <head>The Great CHARTER of the LIBERTIES of ENGLAND, Granted to the People of the ſame, <hi>By King</hi> HENRY <hi>the third;</hi> And accorded between him and them in diverſe full <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ENRY, <hi>by the Grace of God, King of</hi> England, <hi>Lord of</hi> Ireland, <hi>Duke of</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie, <hi>and</hi> Guyen, <hi>and Earl of</hi> Angeow. <hi>To all Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Earls, Barons, Sheriffs, Provoſts, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; And to all Bailiffs, and our faithfull Subjects, which ſhall ſee this preſent</hi> Charter, <hi>greeting.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Know ye, that We, to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Almightie God, and for the ſalvation of the ſouls of our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111570:4"/>Progenitours, and Succeſſours, Kings of</hi> England, <hi>to the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of holy church, and amendment of our Realm of</hi> England; <hi>of Our meer free will, have given and granted to all Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Abbots, Priors, Earls, Barons, and to all Free-men of this Realm of</hi> England <hi>for evermore.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt, We have granted to God, and by this preſent Charter have confirmed for Vs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 1. Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> 
                     <hi>and our Heirs for evermore; That the church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>ſhall be free, and ſhall have all her whole rights, and liberties invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable: We have granted alſo, and given to all Free-men of our Realm, for Vs, and Our Heirs for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, theſe Liberties under-writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to have and to hold, to them, and to their heirs, of Vs, and Our heirs, for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here be four rehearſals</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke) of four notable cauſes of the making this Law.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> Fol. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>Firſt, for the honour of God. Secondly, for the health of the Kings ſoul. Thirdly, For the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of the church. Fourthly, for the amendment of the Kingdom. And all granted to all ſubjects, and their heirs, from the King and his heirs for evermore; That the great Charter might live, and take effect in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111570:4"/>of ages for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>The laſt of theſe cauſes which the L. <hi>C.</hi> in his Preamble calleth the ends for which this Charter was made, being for the amendment of the Realm, was (ſaith the L. <hi>C.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt chapter of <hi>confirmatio Chart.</hi> fol. 529.) to amend great miſchiefs, and inconveniences, which oppreſſed the whole Realm before the making of both Charters, <hi>viz.</hi> This, and the Charter of the Forreſt, which (ſaith the L. <hi>C.</hi> in his Preface) were declarative Acts of the old Common-Law of the Land, and no introductives of any new Law. If the miſchiefs, and inconveniencies of the Realm were great before the ſaid Acts were made to declare the Laws of the land, which formerly the lawyers reſerved to themſelves, till then undeclared? Were there not greater ſince thoſe Acts were made, and the Lawes thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and ſince the accord of King and People, to keep the ſame invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, when, and as often as they were violated by Kings, and their Counſel, learned in the Laws? As hereafter ſhall appear.</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:111570:5"/>
                  <q>
                     <hi>We,<note place="margin">Cap. 8. Debt. Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. Suer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> nor Our Bailiffs ſhall not ſeiſe any lands, or rent, for any debt, as long as the preſent goods, and chattels of the debtors do ſuffice to pay the debt, and the debtor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be ready to ſatisfie: Therefore ſhall neither the pledges of the debtor be diſtrained, as long as the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple debtor is ſufficient for payment of the debt; and if the principal deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor fail in paiment of the debt, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nought wherewith to pay, or will not, where he is able enough; Then the pledges ſhall anſwer for the debt; and if they will, they ſhall have the lands, and rents of the debtor, until they be ſatisfied of that which they before paid for him, except that the debtor can ſhew himſelf to be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the ſuerties.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) <hi>spoken in the politique capacitie of a King,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>M. C.</hi> fol. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to his Succeſſours. And by Bailiffs, are meant Sheriffs, who write</hi> Baliva mea, <hi>&amp;c. And by the words</hi> ſhall not ſeiz <hi>is expreſſed the Kings Grace, who by the Common-Law had Execution againſt his Debtors bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, lands, and goods. And by the Statute of</hi> 33. Hen. 8. cap. 9. <hi>The Sheriff is to inquire</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and to extend all Lands, Goods, Chattels.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> take and impriſon the Bodies, as by that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111570:5"/>Stat. appeareth, and as the daily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ſheweth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>If We extend to Succeſſors, even to King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Why not longer? If <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was to live for ever, Why not hitherto? If the King of his Grace remitted by this Act the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution which the Common Law gave him before againſt his Debtors, Bodies, Lands, and Goods, in caſe of having nought wherewith to pay, through decay of their eſtates by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable neceſſities; then the Kings Debtors obtained of the Kings Grace as much Liberty for their bodies, as this King gave to all his free ſubjects by the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of this Act, <hi>viz. No Free man</hi> &amp;c. And for his Eſtate, as much as the proverb ſaith; <hi>Where nothing is to be bad, the King looſeth his due.</hi> If the King did not remit ſo much by this Act, then did he gain thereby more than he gave, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the opinion of all Lawyers, that ſay, All Acts of Parliament are to be expounded for the benefit of the Subject. And what, and how did he gain? but contrary to his Honour, much more to his Grace, when two more of his ſubjects were hedged in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111570:6"/>by this Act, as Pledges to pay for his undone Debtor, and to undoe themſelves and their families by the bargain. And (their eſtates being too little to pay their own debts) their Creditours muſt ſee the King firſt ſerved our of the ſame, to their no ſmall prejudice, if not undoing, whereby many are injured through one mans occaſion. If therefore this Act ought to be conſtrued for the honour of the King, and benefit of the ſubject (as I believe it ought, and the L. <hi>C.</hi> ſaith, others have thought ſo) it followeth, That the Statute of the 33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.9. was made (as many more were before and ſince) againſt <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and not onely againſt Kings honour, and grace, but alſo their Oathes, to the undoing of multitudes of their ſubjects, which was ungracious for their Counſel learned in the Laws, to give advice, or aſſent to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch Laws, or when made, to allow them, much more to maintain them; being that all Judges are to receive <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> for a Plea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Statutes made againſt it. And all Judgements given againſt <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> are, and ought to be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111570:6"/>void; (as appeareth in the L. <hi>C.</hi> preamble) And all ſuch Statutes as were made before the 42. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. againſt <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> were then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plealed: and (as I conceive) all made ſo ſince, are repealed by the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Right, 3. <hi>Car.</hi> that reſtored <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> to its primitive vigor, and conſequently enervated all its opponents.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The City of <hi>London</hi> ſhall have the old Liberties,<note place="margin">Cap. 9. <hi>London</hi> &amp;c.</note> and cuſtoms which it hath been uſed to have. Moreover We will, and grant, that all other Cities, Burroughs, Towns, and the Barr ons of the five Ports, and all other Ports, ſhall have their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and Free-cuſtoms.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Chapter</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) <hi>is excellently interpreted by an ancient Author</hi> (quoting the <hi>Mirrour</hi> in the Margent) <hi>who ſaith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>C.</hi> upon <hi>M. C.</hi> fol. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>that by this Chapter, the Citizens of</hi> London <hi>ought to have their Franchizes, whereof they are inheritable by loyal Title, of the gift, and confirmation of the Kings, which they have not forfetted by any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe; and that they ſhall have their Franchizes, and Cuſtomes, which are ſufferable by right, and not repugnant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111570:7"/>to law: And the ſame interpretation ſerveth for the</hi> Cinque-ports, <hi>and other places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>Doth not this Charter, and chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſufficiently declare, and Lawyers, (though unwillingly, yet plainly) confeſs, that <hi>London</hi> and the reſt, had old Liberties and cuſtomes, and that they are inheritable thereof, and ought ſtill to have the ſame, ſo long and ſo far, as not repugnant to Law, (which I conceive to be this Law, and not any that have been made ſince againſt it?) And do not the ſeveral Charters of <hi>London,</hi> and other Cities and Towns, obtained ſince this Law, declare further what thoſe Liberties, and Cuſtoms were? And if the Kings learned Councel have conſented that he ſhould grant, or Profeſſors of the Law adviſed Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners, or any other Citizens, to ask things repugnant to this Law, and prevailed with both parties? Have they not miſled both parties? And though they have ſo done often; yet in this caſe, doth not the Statute of the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> 7. chap. 7. help the offendors with leſs danger than the forfeiture of their Cuſtoms, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111570:7"/>Liberties, if they offend eſpecially but in thoſe points, which their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers ſo much miſadviſed them to ask, and the Kings, him to grant?</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Common-Pleas ſhall not follow Our Court,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ca. 11. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Pleas.</note> 
                     <hi>but ſhall be holden in ſome place certain.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Before this Statute</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) Common-Pleas <hi>might have been holden in the</hi> Kings-Bench,<note place="margin">L.<hi>C.</hi> upon <hi>M.C.</hi> fol. 22, 23.</note> 
                     <hi>and all Writs returnable unto the ſame</hi> Bench; <hi>And becauſe the Court was holden</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Rege, <hi>and followed the Kings Court, and removable at the Kings will, the Returns were</hi> Ubicum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus in Angliâ <hi>whereupon many diſcontinuances enſued, and great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Jurors, charges of Parties, and delay of Juſtice; for this cauſe this Statute was made,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And Pleas of the Crown were divided into high Treaſon, Mispriſion of Treaſon, Petty Treaſon, Fellony,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and limited to this Court, becauſe</hi> contrà coronam, &amp; dignitatem, <hi>&amp;c. So that of theſe</hi> (the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith) <hi>the</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas <hi>cannot hold Plea. But to ſhew that</hi> Common-Pleas <hi>may be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the</hi> Kings-Bench, he ſaith. <hi>That
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111570:8"/>the King is out of this Statute, and may ſue in that Court.</hi> Secondly, <hi>if a man be</hi> in Cuſtodia, <hi>any other may lay upon him any Action of debt, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or the like perſonal Action, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he that is</hi> in Cuſtodia, <hi>ought to have the priviledge of that Court And this Act taketh not away the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of any Court.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>any Action that is</hi> Quare vi &amp; Armis, <hi>where the King is to have a Fine, may be ſued in this Court.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins may be removed thither.</hi> Fifthly, (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) <hi>Albeit originally the</hi> Kings-Bench <hi>be reſtrained by this Act, to hold Plea of any Real action yet by a mean, they may; as when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by writ of Error from</hi> Common-Pleas, <hi>thither for neceſſitie, leſt any party that hath right ſhould be without remedie, or that there ſhould be a failer of Juſtice; and therefore Statutes are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be expounded ſo, that there ſhould be no failer of Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>Do not the L. <hi>C.</hi> words, viz. (<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Statute,</hi> &amp;c.) imply, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Statute, <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> ought not to be holden in the <hi>Kins-Bench,</hi> nor all Writs be returnable into the ſame <hi>Beach?</hi> Doth the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111570:8"/>or <hi>Natura brevium</hi> therefore ſhew any Writ for debt returnable to the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> Doth not <hi>Fitz. H. natura brevium</hi> fol. 119. h. <hi>&amp;</hi> k. declare that there is no Writ in Law for debt, but a <hi>Juſticies,</hi> which is a judicial Commiſſion to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff to determine the matter, <hi>Nè am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plius indè clamorem audiamuus:</hi> So that the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> ought not to be troubled with the matter at all? or if an Original returnable to the <hi>Common-Pleas?</hi> Doth not that Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal declare it ſelf to be a Summons? And doth not M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Kitchen</hi> in his <hi>Ret. brev.</hi> fol. 4. <hi>Tit. com. bank,</hi> declare, that Summons, Atachment, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringas, ſucceſtively diſtant fifteen days one after another, is the onely Proces at Common Law? The <hi>Kings-Beach,</hi> and <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> ought to practiſe by the Common Law, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and accord of the King and People; declared and injoyned to be obſerved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable, and immutable for ever. Did ever any Judge of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> or <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> adviſe, or conſent to the making any Statute, or Law to the contrarie, (being ſworn to execute and maintain <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:111570:9"/>as anon ſhall appear all were, or ought to be) and was not perjured? Did, or doth any Judge of any Court of <hi>Record,</hi> obſerve any ſuch Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo made; or practice, or ſuffer to be practiſed (where he hath authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) any ſuits or proceedings contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and was, and is he not perjured? Doth not the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> ſtill ſhew, that thence doth iſſue no other Writ for debt, than a Bill of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> or Latitar, which expreſs themſelves to be for Treſpaſs? Are not thoſe Writs ſtill returnable <hi>ubicunquè ſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus,</hi> and the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> therefore ſtill removeable at the Kings will? whereupon (as ſaith the L. <hi>Coke</hi>) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſcontinuances enſue, and great trouble of Jurours, charges of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and delay of Juſtice: for which cauſes (he ſaith) this Statute was made. How doth this Statute (if therefore made) prevent ſuch diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuances, trouble, charges, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of Juſtice, but by declaring, that <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> ſhall not follow the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> How contradictorie to himſelf is the L. <hi>Coke</hi> then, when he laboureth to make <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> lawfull to be holden in the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111570:9"/>And if (as he ſaith) the <hi>Pleas</hi> of the Crown were divided into high Treaſon, Miſpriſion of Treaſon, Petty Treaſon, Fellonie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; limited to the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> becauſe <hi>cont. Coron. &amp; dign. Regis;</hi> ſo that of theſe (ſaith he) the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> cannot hold <hi>Plea.</hi> By what Juſtice can he deſire to hold <hi>Common-Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as</hi> in the <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> unleſs becauſe more gainfull, (as when he was ſupplanted by his ſucceſſour, under colour of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> to the <hi>Kings-Beach,</hi> he paſſionately expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the difference, ſaying, That he was called from the warm kitchen, to the cold hall:) and that therefore he deſired to reduce Juſtice to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, rather than his deſire to Juſtice? But let us examine his Arguments for that purpoſe. Firſt, (ſaith he) The King is out of this Stature. How? out of this Statute, which above all other, the King was ſworn to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and obey, and to violate was perjurie, and puniſhable in all men without regard of perſons, and no leſs in the Lo. <hi>C.</hi> to ſay and write o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe? But (ſaith he) the King might ſue in his <hi>Bench.</hi> And ſo might he in any Court of <hi>Record</hi> which he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111570:10"/>pleaſed; for all ſuch Courts are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his, and have power under him, to adminiſter Juſtice to all men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Commiſſions and Charters, as well as the <hi>Kings Bench;</hi> and therefore he had his Atturneys, and Sollicitours, attending many ſuch Courts. Secondly, (ſaith he) if a man be <hi>in cuſtodia,</hi> any other may lay upon him any action of debt <hi>&amp;c.</hi> becauſe (ſaith he) that he that is <hi>in cuſtodia,</hi> ought to have the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of that Court. Now if a man be <hi>in cuſtodia</hi> for Fellonie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and an Action for Debt, &amp;c. be laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, ſhall his priviledge in being <hi>in cuſtodia</hi> keep him from hanging (if he deſerve it) till he pay the debt? or if he be hanged, and have any goods, ſhall the Creditour be paid his debt out of the ſame; or if he have any lands, out of the <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheat?</hi> I believe not. If a man be not <hi>in cuſtodia,</hi> but a Juſtice of Peace, or a Grand-Juror, attending Seſſions in <hi>Cumberland</hi> or <hi>Cornwall,</hi> what priviledge of this Court doth he need? If he be arreſted there, upon a Writ of treſpaſs, when he is guiltie of none, is he not more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced than priviledged by this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111570:10"/>Court? when he is forced to appear in this Court for treſpaſs, and nothing declared againſt him for any ſuch matter, ought he not to be diſmiſſed for that matter, with coſts, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, anſwerable to his diſgrace and expences, though arreſted at the Kings ſuit? Shall the King do any man wrong? how then doth the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xim hold, that he cannot? Shall this Court abuſe his name, to wrong his Subject? Is not Injuſtice, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie in a Judge ſworn to do Juſtice? Is not all againſt <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> and truth, which is, God himſelf? If not ſo diſmiſſed, ſhall a declaration be admitted againſt him upon an Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal for debt, where neither ſuch Writ, nor cauſe belong? And ſhall the Defendant be inforced to wait upon his Bail for treſpaſs, to anſwer that Declaration? is not that more Injuſtice? And moreover, if that Writ, or the Return thereof be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, (as all, or moſt Originals direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi> or <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi> are; aſwel by Clerks of this Court, and ſo filed upon Record here as by Attorneys in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas,</hi> there;) ſhall that Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be admitted to ſay, that the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111570:11"/>Defendant is <hi>in cuſtodia,</hi> (which is falſe;) and be made a Record, which would be accounted the next truth to Goſpel? And ſhall not the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant be admitted to plead <hi>Mag. Ch.</hi> againſt the juriſdiction of the Court, and ſuch lying Records? If not; is not all this more Injuſtice and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie? Shall Judges give Judgements upon fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Records (except to burn them, and puniſh the makers, and cauſers) and ſhall not they be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and called falſe Judges, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers; and their judgements falſe judgements and perjuries? Shall they, that commit Debtors into their Marſhals cuſtodie, upon ſuch judgements by their priviledge (as they call it,) ſay that this Statute doth nor take away ſuch priviledges, when the Lo. <hi>C.</hi> himſelf ſaith, that all Statutes ought to be expounded ſo, that there ſhould be no failer of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and this Statute, being <hi>M. Ch.</hi> (chief of all Statutes) and all its Confirmations ſay, that equal juſtice ought to be done to all men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regard of perſons? What Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or cuſtom did, or can give any priviledge to any Court to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie? What benefit of priviledge
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111570:11"/>hath the Debtor, that is ſo commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by this Court, and its priviledge, but his undoing, and his families, and often his untimely death by famin, and miſerie? Is not that ſo occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by the rigour, and illegalitie of this Court, an offence of the higheſt nature, of Munther and Perjurie? Who gaineth any thing by this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, but the Court, and their Marſhal in extorted Fees, to the dammage of both Creditor and Debtor, and often the ruin of both or either? Why therefore doth the L. <hi>C.</hi> call it a priviledge to the party in Cuſtodie, when it appeareth to be no benefir, but prejudice unto him, and that more aggravated, to have more Actions laid upon him for more debts occaſioned (perhaps) by his impriſonment? What law, or reaſon requireth any priviledge to any man for debt, ſince this Statute in the 29 chapter, freeth all mens bodies from impriſonment, untill they be lawfully tried by their Peers? and no law, but an abortive Statute made 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. and repealed in the 42 of the ſame King (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) gave an Arreſt againſt Debtors but Merchants and Accomptants?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111570:12"/>and a Statute made in the ſaid 25 year of the ſaid King, gave the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors two parts of all their Debtors lands, &amp; all thei goods (except the beaſts of their plough) for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their debts, which Statute is ſtill in force, and daily executed accordingly? As for Accomptants, Debtors, and Tennants to the King, that are ſo indeed, if the Court of <hi>Exchequer</hi> be thought proper for them; why ſhould others that are not ſuch indeed, be ſheltered to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend or countenanced to offend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that pretence? And as for Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of any Court, why ought not they to ſue, and be ſued by their At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneys in other Courts than their own, ſince it is unnatural for any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to ſuffer any of its Members (though never ſo corrupt) to be put to any ſmart, which it may avoid? And may not, nay ought not every juſt Court avoid ſuch ſuits, and the ſuſpition of their injuſtice by enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining them, and proceeding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, by leaving them to the juſtice of other Courts of competent judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as all other Courts do leave their Members to the mercy of the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter?</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111570:12"/>or may not, nay ought not all Courts of judicature within their juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, determine the cauſes of all ſuch Members of the Courts at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> as ſhall be found, and arreſted within their juriſdictions, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any Writs of priviledge, or other Writs to remove them, before they be determined; rather than the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> may ſend for the Members of every Court, to be juſtified by them? For who can ſay, he hath ever found any juſtice there againſt any priviledged man? And how many that be no Members of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Court there indeed, are ſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, as ſubordinate to ſome ill Member, or other there, and have their Law for nothing, to bring Fees and gain to one or other of thoſe courts, out of honeſtmens purſes and Eſtates, againſt whom they can ſhew no colour of right any where, but where they know they ſhall be favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and their Adverſaries oppreſſed? And how many men of good Eſtates have been, and daily are, not onely oppreſſed, but undone by that means? Thirdly, for Treſpaſs, <hi>vi &amp; Armis;</hi> Is it but a common-Plea, and conſequently proper to all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111570:13"/>courts of Record, and rather to be tryed within that juriſdiction where the offence is committed, than elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? And hath not the King his Fines impoſed and levyed by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of all ſuch courts, as wel as by the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> Fourthly, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevins, may they not as well be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to, and determined by the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> as in the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> Fifthly, what meaneth the Lord by his words, <hi>viz. [Originally reſtrained]</hi> but that the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> is reſtrained from having any origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Writs Returnable thither in <hi>Real</hi> Pleas,? And is it not as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from originals in <hi>Perſonal Pleas,</hi> that are as <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> as <hi>Real,</hi> by this Statute? Or by what other Statute, Law, or Preſident, is it inabled to have any originals re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnable to it for debt, when the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter and <hi>Ret. brevium</hi> have no ſuch Preſidents, as aforeſaid? Is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the practice of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> for debt, unjuſt, and perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, as aforeſaid? and moreover a faint Action, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the priſoners for debt in that Court have lately ſet forth by their Petition to the Lord General, and his Officers concerning this matter.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111570:13"/>
                  <q>
                     <hi>A Free-man ſhall not be ameirced for a ſmall fault,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Caput 14. <hi>Ameir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>but after the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of the fault, and for a greater fault, after the manner thereof, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to him his contenement, or Freehold: And a Merchant ſhall be likewiſe ameirced, ſaving to him his Merchandize: And any other Villain than Durs, ſhall be likewiſe ameirced, ſaving his Wainage, if he fall into Our mercy: And none of the ſaid Ameirciaments ſhall be aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. but by the caths of honeſt men of the Viſionage: Carls, and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons ſhall not be ameirced, but by their Peers, and after the quantitie of their treſpaſs. No man of the Church ſhall be ameirced after the rate of his ſpiritual benefice, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the rate of his lay teuement, and the quantitie of his treſpaſs.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Free-man here,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lord Cook upon <hi>Magna Charta</hi> fol. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>hath a ſpecial underſtanding</hi> (ſaith the L. C.) <hi>and is taken for a Free-holder; and this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by this clauſe,</hi> Salvo contene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento ſuo. <hi>viz. Saving his Free-hold,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This Act extendeth to Ameircia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not to Fines impoſed by any Court of Juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Free-men are not intended to officers, or miniſters, or officers of juſtice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Writ of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derata miſericordia, <hi>giveth remedie to the Partie that is exceſſively ameir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Albeit the Law of</hi> England
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111570:14"/>
                     <hi>is a Law of mercy, yet it is now turned to a ſhadow; for where by the wiſdom of the Law, theſe Ameirciaments were inſtituted, to deter both Domandants from unjuſt ſuits, and Defendants from unjuſt defences, which was the cauſe in former times of fewer ſuits,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If amerciaments were inſtituted to deter Plantiffs from unjuſt ſuits,<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> and Defendants from unjuſt defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and were the cauſes of fewer ſuits in former times; how comes the Law turned to a ſhaddow in the Lord <hi>Cokes</hi> time? when in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and <hi>Cmmon-Pleas,</hi> am ercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were as frequent, and greivous as in any other time, and ſuits no fewer, nay more numerous than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, (as Records of both Courts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) unleſs he means that all the Writs in the Regiſter, and <hi>Natura bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium,</hi> both original, and judicial, (whereby ſuits were determined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt neighbours friendly at home) became uſeleſs, ſince <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> &amp;c. carried all to <hi>Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?</hi> And that there injuſtice ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed under the name and habit of juſtice, remunerated the litigious ſupporters of her being, with ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111570:14"/>ſhares of her ſpoils, that though ſhe trebled their amerciaments, ſhe made them alwaies gainers; unleſs when to ſatisfie their revenge, rather than their purſes, they commuted their monies for counſels, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, to undo the oppoſers of their malice, whereby both parties became looſers, and often ruined; and injuſtice onely remained the gainer, and increaſed her kingdom (as the Divel doth his) by ſuch ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and made more ſuits for <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> than all the Courts of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and their Judges, Lawyers, and Attorneys there, ſhall wear out while they live, without extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry helps of their ſervants.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No town, or Free-man ſhall be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to make Bridges, or banks,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">C. 15. Bridg. Banks.</note> 
                        <hi>but ſuch as of old time, and of right have been accuſtomed to make them in the time of King</hi> Henry <hi>our Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>No Banks ſhall be defended hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">C. 16. Banks.</note> 
                        <hi>but ſuch as were in defence in the time of King</hi> Henry <hi>our Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, by the ſame places, and the ſame hounds, as were wont to be in his time.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Both the next precedent chapters ſufficiently expound themſelves, ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111570:15"/>that the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſpeaketh no more to this matter, but that the <hi>Mirrour</hi> ſaith, <hi>That diver Rivers and their Banks were in his time appropriated, and blocked up by divers perſons, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar common-fiſhings, which were wont to be uſed there in the time of King</hi> H. 2. And I believe, there are many more ſo done, more lately, which Commiſſioners for Sewers ſhall do well to look to.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>No Sheriff,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. 17. Pleas Crown</note> 
                     <hi>Conſtable, Eſchea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Coroner, or any other our Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, ſhall hold Pleas of the Crown.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One miſchief before this Statute,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>M. C.</hi> 30.</note> 
                     <hi>was</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) <hi>That no Court, but the Kings chief Court, could command Biſhops to give their clergy to ſuch as ought to have it: another cauſe was, That the life of a man ought to be tryed before Judges of learning, and experience of the Laws of the Realm; for</hi> Ignorantia Judicis, eſt ſaepenumerò calamitas innocentis. <hi>Theſe are the reaſons that the Lord</hi> Coke <hi>alledgeth, why ſome Pleas of the Crown were taken from Sheriffs, Caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans, Eſcheators, Coronors, and Bailiffs, under which names</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111570:15"/>comprehended all inferiour Judges, Juſtices, and Courts of Juſtice: albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it be provided by the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chap. of</hi> Mag. Charta, <hi>That the Barons of the five Ports ſhould have all their Liberties and Cuſtoms. Theſe general words</hi> (ſaith he again) <hi>muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſuch Liberti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s and Cuſtoms, as are not afterwards in the ſame</hi> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>by expreſs words taken away, and aſſumed to the Crown.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Might not the Kings inferior Courts command ordinary Miniſters to give men their Clergie?<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> And might not that ſerve before <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> as it is uſual ſince? For ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, or never in our memories, did Biſhops themſelves attend any court for that ſervice: and now, ſhould they be neceſſary onely for that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment? So the Kings Court would be onely to command them: but if Biſhops may be ſpared, why may not that Court for that cauſe? And if by this <hi>Charter</hi> the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed ſome Pleas of the crown from thoſe that formerly had them; dor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> et follow, that he reſumed all Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> from thoſe that formerly had them? And if under the name of Bailiffs be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111570:16"/>comprehended all Judges, and Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, are not the Judges of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Pleas</hi> and Barons of the <hi>Exchec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer</hi> ſo comprehended? And are none of them of ſuch learning and experience in the Laws of the Realm, to try the life of a man, as Judges of the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> Or elſe, why are they ſent for Goal-deliveries, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel as Judges of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> are? Was it not provided by the 9. chapter of <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> That <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and other Cities, Burroughs and Towns, as well as the Barons of the five Ports, and other Ports ſhould have their Liberties and Free-Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms? Are all theſe now reſumed by this 17. chap? Who can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſo? Or what meaneth the L. <hi>C.</hi> by his riddles? Shall <hi>Magna Charta</hi> contradict it ſelf, though the Lord <hi>C.</hi> would, and doth here and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? Are not Commiſſions of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> uſual for Tryal of mens lives, where Judges of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> cannot reach, or dare not go? Doth not <hi>London</hi> and other Corporations execute their Charters by their Recorders, when the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> gives them leave; and then do not the Judges of the <hi>Kings</hi>-Bench
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111570:16"/>grant that ſuch Judges may be as learned, and experienced in the Laws as themſelves, for the Trying of mens lives? Are not mens lives Tryable for matter of Fact, and not of Law, (except Treaſons that reach to thoughts?) Are not Jurors the Judges of matters of Fact? What great learning, or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in Law is requiſite for a Judge to pronounce the ſentence of death, where the verdict hath determined the life? But how many true men have been hanged, and thieves ſaved by Judges interpoſing, and obtrud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their peſtifferous pretended learning and experience in the Laws between the weak conſciences of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Jurors, and the truth? which kind of Jurors they make Sheriffs return for ſuch purpoſes, when they may have ſuch returned as know the Facts, and have ſounder learning and experience in expreſs Law than themſelves.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>All Wears from henceforth be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly put down by</hi> Thames,<note place="margin">C. 23. <hi>Wear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>and</hi> Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, <hi>and throughout all</hi> England, <hi>but onely by the Sea-coaſts.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:111570:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was specially given in charge by the Justices in Eyre</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>C.</hi>) <hi>that all Juries ſhould inquire of all ſuch as Fiſhed with wears and Dams:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>C.</hi> upon <hi>M. C.</hi> fol. 38.</note> 
                     <hi>and it appeareth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by</hi> Glandvil lib. 9. c. 11. <hi>That when any thing is unjuſtly occupied within the Kings demeſne, or obſtructed in publick waies; or Rivers, turned off their right channels, or Citie-streets built upon; and in general, as often as any nuſance to the Kings holding, or his High-way, or to any Citie, is committed; That is a purpresture,</hi> viz. <hi>an Inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whereby one in chroacheth, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that ſeveral to himſelf, which ought to be common to all, or many; and every publick River, or stream, the Kings High way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If Wears be nuſances (as I am ſure they are) throughout <hi>England,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> and <hi>Wales;</hi> and if Commiſſioners for Sewers, and Juſtices of Peace for want of them, be ſufficiently autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to reform ſuch wrongs, and do not, becauſe chief doers thereof, or ſharers in the unlawful gain made thereof themſelves: why not Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Eyer imployed to execute their charge, for the general amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111570:17"/>thereof, for the publick good?</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>One Meaſure of Wine ſhall be throughout our Realm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. 29. Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>and one mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Corn,</hi> viz. <hi>according to the Quarter of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Haberjects, <hi>that is to ſay, two yards within the liſt, and as it is of Weights, ſo ſhall it be of Meaſures.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Act concerning Meaſures,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>Cok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> upon <hi>M. C.</hi> fol. 49.</note> 
                     <hi>and Weights, that there ſhould be one Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and one Weight through</hi> England, <hi>is grounded upon the Law of God,</hi> Deut. 25. <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>And this by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliaments hath been often enacted, but never effected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If Weights and Meaſures through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>England</hi> ought to be one,<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> and that not onely by the Law of God (as the Lord <hi>C.</hi> inſtanceth) but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by this <hi>Charter</hi> of Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and the People; Why did not the Lord <hi>C.</hi> (being chief Juſtice of <hi>England</hi>) ſworn to do Law, and Juſtice too, and between King and People, (as partly before did, and hereafter further ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear he was, or ought to have been) ſee this point of Juſtice, (ſo highly
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111570:18"/>required by the Law of God, and ſo mutually agreed upon by the Kings of this Land, and their Subjects) du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed?</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Nothing ſhall henceforth be given for a Writ of Inquiſition,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ca. 16. <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>nor taken of him that prayeth the Inquiſition of Life, or Member, but it ſhall be granted freely.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Writ of Inquiſition,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>C.</hi> upon <hi>M. C.</hi> fol. 42.</note> viz. De odio &amp; atia, <hi>anciently called</hi> De bono &amp; malo, <hi>&amp;c. which the Common-Law gave a man that was impriſoned, though it were for the moſt odious cauſe, for the death of a man, for which (without the Kings Writ) he could not be bailed; Yet the Law fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the Libertie and Freedom of a man from Impriſonment,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>until the Juſtices in Eyre ſhould come, at what time he was to be tryed; he might ſue out this VVrit directed to the Sheriff,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>If a Writ <hi>De odio &amp; atia</hi> was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Common-Law,<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> to a man Impriſoned for the moſt odious cauſe, even for the death of a man; and if the Common-Law favoured
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111570:18"/>the Liberty of a man Impriſoned, ſo that he ſhould be Bailed for ſuch a Fact, until Juſtices in Eyre ſhould Try him; Why not ſuch a Writ ſtill? Since <hi>odium</hi> (which the Lord <hi>C.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fineth to be <hi>hatred</hi>) and <hi>atia (malice)</hi> and Priſoners for thoſe cauſes are no ſcanter now, than in former times? And why not Juſtices in Eyre (made ſince competent Judges by Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion without Writs) to determine ſuch matters, which before they could but inquire of by Writs (as the Lord <hi>C.</hi> ſaith elſewhere, though he ſaith here to try them,) imployed for that ſervice? And now if it be Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a Judge of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> to determine a debt, and to grant an <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> for money, to bring the Priſoner before him to put in Bail; Why ſhould he take money for the Writ, and refuſe ſufficient Bail tendred after Oath made of their ſufficiency, without the plantiffs conſent? Nay after acceptation of the Bail, Why refuſe to File it?</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>No Free-man ſhall be taken,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ca 2.9. <hi>No Free man</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>or impriſoned, or be disſeiſed of his Freehold, or Liberties, or Free Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, or be Outlawed, or Exiled, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111570:19"/>any way otherwiſe deſtroyed; nor we ſhall not paſs upon him, but by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full judgement of his Peers, or by the Law of the Land; we ſhall ſell to no man, we ſhall denie, or deferre to no man, either Iuſtice, or Right.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Free-man extends to Villains both Sexes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> Fol. 46 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> &amp;c. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this Chapter, as out of a root, many fruitfull branches of the Law of</hi> England <hi>have ſprung. It containeth nine ſeveral Branches: Firſt, That no man be taken or impriſoned, but by the Law of the Land;</hi> viz. <hi>The Common-Law, Statute-Law, or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of</hi> England, &amp;c. <hi>Secondly, No man ſhall be disſeiſed,</hi> viz. <hi>put out of his Freehold, that is, Land, Livelihood, or Liberties, or free Cuſtoms, ſuch as belong to him by his free Birth-right; unleſs it be by the lawfull judgement, and verdict of his equals, or by the Law of the Land, that is (to ſpeak it once for all) by the Due courſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Law. Thirdly, no man ſhall be Outlawed, or put off the Law,</hi> viz. <hi>Deprived of the benefit of it, unleſs he be Outlawed by the Law of the Land. Fourthly, No man ſhall be exiled,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>unleſs according to the Law of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111570:19"/>Land. Fifthly, No man ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed</hi> &amp;c. <hi>unleſs by verdict, or accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of the Land. Sixthly, No man ſhall be condemned,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but by the judgement of his equals, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of the Land. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venthly, We ſhall ſell to no man, Juſtice, or right. Eighthly, We ſhall denie no man Juſtice or right. And Ninthly, We ſhall deferre no man Juſtice or Right,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> If no man ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or impriſoned but by the Law of the Land, <hi>viz.</hi> the Common-Law, Statute-Law, and Cuſtoms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> is it not cleared by our Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulations before upon the 11. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, that Debtors are taken, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the Common-Law of <hi>England,</hi> declared by <hi>Mag. Chart.</hi> contrarie to the chief Statute of <hi>England,</hi> which is <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and which the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith, ſhould live (as was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by King and people) for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? And contrarie to the Cuſtom of <hi>England</hi> declared by <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> and alſo by the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the impriſonment of any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111570:20"/>Debtours, but onely the Kings. And are not Debtors, other than the Kings, ſo impriſoned, as well elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, as in the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if no man ſhall be disſeiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> put out of his Freehold; that is to ſay, His Livelihood, Liberties, or Free-Cuſtoms, ſuch as belong to him by his Birth-right; unleſs it be by the lawfull judgement, and verdict of his equals, or by the Law of the Land, that is to ſay, (once for all) by Due courſe, and Proces of Law. Are not Debtors disſeiſed of their Livelihood, Libertie, and Freedom which belonged unto them as their Freehold by Birth right, when they are impriſoned in <hi>London, Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> or elſewhere, by Arreſts, and Actions for Debt, whether due, or not, upon meer ſuggeſtions of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, not ſo much to Judges, as to Catch-pols, without any judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or verdict of their equals, and without Due courſe, or Proces of Law, which ſhould be Summons, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment, and Diſtringas, before any Arreſt, as aforeſaid? Are they not taken in the Countrey from their Ploughs, which are their Livelihood, and their Countreys, and their Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111570:20"/>by Birth-right; by vagant Bum-baylies, and impriſoned there, till they give bail to appear at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter;</hi> and thence, inſtead of being remanded home to their ſweet Farm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, large fields, and induſtrious Agricultures; are they not ſent to ſtinking Goals, cloſe dungeons, and idle Monk-cels, whereby they are allowed little more ground to walk upon while they live, than might ſerve them to lie under, when they are dead? Are not all the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>England,</hi> and their free-cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Officers, (that ſhould do them juſtice at home) disſeiſed of their Freeholds by Birth-right, and Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, before and ſince <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> when they are prevented of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of juſtice in execution of their Offices to which they were ſworn, (and heritable ſucceſſively from their Anceſtours by Cuſtom long before <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and ſince confirmed by the ſame, and by Charters dated before, and ſince) by <hi>Certioraries, Habeas Corpus,</hi> &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Judgement; and pretence of Errors after; and though never any proved, or aſſigned, yet the cauſes never remanded, but detained at
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111570:21"/>
                     <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the uſual correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of pretended Errours, is not by making any thing that is crooked, ſtraight; but all that is ſtraight, crooked; ſo that both Plantiffs, and Defendants give their titles for loſt in a miſt commonly; but he that hath the wrongfull poſſeſſion, and money, holdeth it; and he that hath the right, and no money, goes to his grave without it? Are not all the People of <hi>England</hi> disſeiſed of their Freehold, Liberties, Franchiſes, and Free cuſtoms, when they are depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of that juſtice which they ought to have adminiſtred amongſt them at home, by virtue of the Kings Writs (original for Enquiries, and judicial for Determinations) directed to Sheriffs of their own choiſe, in their own Counties, or Stewards of Hundreds, and Court-Barons, in their precincts, where the Free-holders themſelves are Judges themſelves, by ancient Common Laws, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of <hi>England,</hi> before <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and by it declared, and confirmed unto them as aforeſaid? Can Writs of treſpaſs executed for debt; or Capiaſes, grounded upon counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited Originals, be conſtrued by any
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111570:21"/>Law, to be due Proces of Law? Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Are men lawfully Outlawed upon Exigents for debt, grounded upon a repealed Statute? and are not all Debtors that are Outlawed, ſo Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed? Are men lawfully Outlawed, that are Outlawed upon Exigents, grounded upon <hi>Summonitus,</hi> or <hi>Non eſt inventus,</hi> counterfeitly returned by Attorneys, who at the time of the return were no Sheriffs, or compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent officers? and are not all, or moſt Debtors, and Treſpaſſers, that are Outlawed in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> ſo Outlawed? Are men lawfully Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawed upon any Exigents, that are Outlawed without the judgement of the Coroners of the Countie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are Outlawed? Are the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roners of any Countie now adays, preſent at every, or any Countie, when, and where men are Outlawed? Are not their names nevertheleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned as Judges of every Outlary unknown to them, for the moſt part, or all? Are not thoſe Returns falſe, and forged? and are ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, the due courſe, and Proces of Law? How many thouſands of the Free-men of <hi>England</hi> are Outlawed yearly, by ſuch means? and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111570:22"/>of them undone, before they can reverſe them? How many are impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned thereupon, and have all their eſtates ſeiſed for the King, by She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs choſen without the conſent of the People? and often ſuch as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe their Offices, to gain by ſuch means? How many Outlawries year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are ſo clandeſtinely carried, that the parties ſo Outlawed, can hear nothing thereof, before they be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, and their eſtates deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as aforeſaid? How many are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther damnified by ſuch Outlawries, procured of purpoſe, to debar them of their juſt ſuits in all Courts, until they reverſe them? How chargeable are reverſals thereof? What lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is it, or what honour, for the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to make un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull proſit of ſuch unlawfull pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes? Cannot the Judges at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> be contented to have coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Returns of their Originals in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> but they muſt alſo have the like Returns of their Exigents throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Are not ſuch Returns falſe, and perjurious in the Sheriffs that make them? Is it not ſufficient for Judges, to perjure themſelves, but that they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111570:22"/>muſt animate others to do ſo too, by not puniſhing them, when they know that practiſe? Are not the Sheriffs of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> and all the Coroners of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom made liable by this practiſe to Actions of the Caſe, and to pay coſts and dammages to the parties grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved? Are ſuch Judges, Lawyers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the Peace, or Profit of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, that beget, foment, or ſuffer the cauſes of ſuch Actions, cauſeleſly, but for their own ends and gains? Are ſuch Courts to be called, or counted Courts of Juſtice, that maintain any Actions, or Arreſts upon unjuſt grounds, or colour of any miſ-begotten Laws, contrarie to <hi>Mag. Charta?</hi> Are not Aſſaults, Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Reſcues, Riots, and Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, frequent upon ſuch Arreſts? Are not many mens lives loſt, and more hazzarded, and their eſtates ruined thereby? And if a Catch-poll be killed for making, or attempting ſuch unlawfull Arreſt, do not the Judges uſe to adjudge it wilful Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though the wronged party doth but endeavour his juſtifiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence? And have they not begotten a Statute for officers to plead the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111570:23"/>General iſſue, by colour of which they juſtifie themſelves, and their creatures, and condemn the guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs? Are not the cauſers of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as worthy to be hanged, as the doers? Are not they that maintain ſuch Arreſts, to the ſame ends as their Predeceſſors, Imps of the ſame ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? Why therefore their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice deſired, or received in ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? Are not the Releaſes of Errors, which Priſoners are forced to ſeal before they can be inlarged, rather proofs of their guiltineſs, than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittances of ſuch practitioners? Are not their Errors manifeſt to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and gainfull onely to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and hurtfull to the Common-wealth? are ſuch Errors, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, to be called Due courſes, or Proces of Law? Then (to ſpeak once for all) is not the Due courſe, and Proces of Law obſtructed, and perverted? and a wrong courſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, full of Errors, Lies, Forgeries, Perjuries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as alreadie appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and better ſhall hereafter) and cannot Law be executed without ſuch practiſes? Doth not <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and all its confirmations, ſhew how it may? Are not they ſufficient lights,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111570:23"/>and guids for the Due courſe, Proces, and Proceedings which ought to be obſerved, in the right execution of Law? And doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> confeſs them to be ſuch, and that they never miſguided any man, that certainly knew them, and truly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them? Fol. 526. Fourthly, <hi>If no man ſhall be exiled,</hi> &amp;c. Are not Debtors exiled from their Native Soils in <hi>Cumberland,</hi> or <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and from all their wordly comforts, of Wifes, Children, Families, Friends, and Eſtates, both Real, and Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal when called, and forced by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas corpus</hi> &amp;c. to attend Duke <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrey</hi> in <hi>Pauls,</hi> or Judge <hi>Owen</hi> in <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> (as good dead as any Judges living) to hear or diſpatch Suits by the Law of the Land in any way of Juſtice, while the Suitors money laſts; or to relieve them with any Alms, when their Purſes are ſpent? And if at laſt ſent to the <hi>Fleet,</hi> or <hi>Marſhalſey,</hi> where they be pent up as aforeſaid; are they not worſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iled than into <hi>Turkie,</hi> where they may have more Liberty of Land and Sea, and live in leſs Slavery than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Goalers in <hi>England,</hi> and have more hopes to return home again
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111570:24"/>(like Sir <hi>Thomas Shirley,</hi> and many others) than from theſe Hells, whence few find Redemption? Had <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Bullingbrook</hi> been Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Debt here, (as ſuch now are) when he was baniſhed to <hi>France</hi> could he have hoped to be King of <hi>England,</hi> except he had made all his Judges, and Goalers, the beſt ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of all his Uſurpations, as all the cheating Priſoners in theſe places do theirs, as they and their Creditors can beſt tell, by dear, and daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience? Fifthly, <hi>If no man ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>unleſs by Verdict,</hi> &amp;c. Are not all Priſoners for Debt, who are firſt forced themſelves to deſtroy their ſmall Eſtates to buy bread to eat in Idleneſs, and to pay Fees to Goalers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and at laſt to Famiſh in the <hi>Fleet,</hi> or <hi>Marſhalſey,</hi> &amp;c. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed both in Lives, and Eſtates, and their Families to boot, without any Verdict given, or intended for their Lives? Nay are not all the Free-men of <hi>England,</hi> that are, or may be ſubject to Debts, conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubject to the like deſtruction? And worthy ſo long as they ſuffer the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> (contained in the glorious Fabrick of the <hi>Great</hi> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111570:24"/>
                     <hi>of the Liberties of</hi> England, built by their Anceſtors for a perpetual Monument of their care of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and their Liberties for ever) to be thus deſtroyed by an Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Generation of Phariſaical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to the onely knowledge of theſe Laws, which by that pretence, they thus pervert, to deſtroy all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men whom it ſhould ſave, and to ſave all whom it ſhould deſtroy or puniſh; and that for unlawful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and conſiderations tending onely to their own profits, and ends. Sixthly, <hi>If no man ſhall be condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but by the judgement of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals according to the Laws of the Land;</hi> Are not all Debtors that are Famiſhed as aforeſaid, Condemned for their Lives in effect, though but for their Debts in appearance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Verdict of their equals, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, contrary to the Law of the Land? Seventhly, do not all the Judges at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> ſell Juſtice, when they ſell Priſoners for Debt, their Writs of <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> &amp;c. for money, when the King would have all his Writs of Grace to be given to his Subjects <hi>Gratis,</hi> and no Judge to take any Fee, or Reward for any
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111570:25"/>thing but of himſelf? Eightly, Do they not deny Juſtice when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch Writs <hi>Gratis?</hi> Ninthly, Do they not defer Juſtice, when they detain poor men that are Bailable in Priſon, while they have ſufficient men ready to tender for their Bail, till they be forced to borrow money of other friends, and to ſend far, and ſtay long before they can receive it to looſe their Bail in the interim, and be forced to ſeek others; by which delays, their Goalers Fees increaſe, and their Dyer, Lodging, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences draw charges, which they might have ſaved to find Bread for their Wives and Children at home; who perhaps are forced to faſt by that means, and to ſell, or pawn their Cows, or Clothes for this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, this damnable money, thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted by a Judge, for ſcribling his Infamous name to a Writ, which doth but wrap a man, and his cauſe, faſter in his clouches? O Mercileſs, Miſerable, Mercinary Judge! that can neither give, nor lend ſo little as his name, to ſo much goodneſs in Policie, (if not in Charity) to give a man Liberty to breath, and take leave of his Home, upon ſecurity of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111570:25"/>more advantage both to Court, and Party, than his impriſonment to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to his Pinfold. <hi>Radamanth</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf abhorreth ſuch fooliſh covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Do they not defer Juſtice, when by their Writs they cauſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictments, Informations, and juſt Suits Commenced in other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, and more proper Courts in all parts of the Kingdom, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without any Tryal theſe 40 years? How many thouſands of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and heinous Malefactors that ſhould have been puniſhed in, and by their Counties, and Courts at home, have by this means found <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and its Courts, their onely Sanctuaries, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges for none but Eminent, Opulent, Impenitent Offendours? But is not Juſtice denyed, when any Bailable man is denyed to be Bail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Or more, when Bail is accepted upon Oath for its ſufficiency, and is denyed to be Filed, and the Party ſo Bailed in Law, detained Priſoner ſtill, at the Judges, and Planriffs pleaſures? Briefly, Is not the Adminiſtration of all the Law, and Juſtice in <hi>England,</hi> Ingroſſed and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111570:26"/>Monopolized at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the Judges and Courts aſſume to be chief, and do exerciſe a plenary ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction over all others, ſo that they ſuffer none but themſelves to erre, or to abuſe Law; nor any to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh any Juſtice, or to reform any Errors, but onely themſelves, who do pretend to correct all in their <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>checquer-Chamber,</hi> where inſtead of correcting any, they confirm their own; which muſt be all as aforeſaid. Laſtly, is it unknown that they were wont to Buy their Offices of the Kings Servants, and therefore to Sell their Under-Offices to their own Servants, Attorneys, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi> And was not this the Buying and Selling of Juſtice that is yet unpaid for, &amp; had need ſo to be Reformed? Is it any reaſon that any ſhould Buy Juſtice, and not Sell it for gain by the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Is it not Bought to that end? Is it not to that end, Judges neglect to give Attorneys their ancient Oath, whereby they were wont to be Sworn to do no Falſhood, nor cauſe any to be done in their Courts; and if they knew any, to give know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof to the Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that they ſhould increaſe no Fees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111570:26"/>you may read it at large in the latter end of the <hi>Attorneys Academy.</hi> Is it not to the ſame end that Judges neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to give all Plantiffs for Treſpaſs, their Oaths that the Treſpaſs amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to 40<hi rend="sup">f</hi> or more, or elſe let the Suit be Tryed in the Sheriffs Court at home, according to the <hi>Statute of Gloceſter,</hi> 6. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. cap. 8.? And is it not likewiſe to the ſame end, they neglect to take ſecurity of all Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs, to proſecute all Actions with ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or pay Coſts and Damages to the Defendants, if they prove not their Iſſues? which Judges ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed to do, and ſtill ought, before any Declaration be admitted, or Plea required, as ſaith the <hi>Mirror of Juſtice?</hi> fol. 64. b. Is it not to the ſame end the <hi>Chancery</hi> neglecteth to take the Oath of all Complainants to make good their Bills in all points, or pay Coſts and Damages in caſe they fail, and that before any <hi>Sub-poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> be granted them, according to the Statute 15. <hi>H.</hi> 6. cap. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>? And were not all well ended, if all the end were that none were forſworn for Injuſtice, but the chief Juſtices? (though comfortleſs for them to be ſo wretched as to have no aſſociates,)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111570:27"/>is it not the worſe for the People, that their Miniſters which ought to be Sworn as aforeſaid, are not? Whereby old Attorneys without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Perjury, lead young Judges Sworn to what they know not, to do what they ſhould not? as when ſo many ſubtil and lying <hi>Mercuries,</hi> direct ſo many covetous and blind <hi>Cupids</hi> to ſhoot forth their arrows, that they may ſtick them where they pleaſe, and commend the ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for hitting the marks that yield them the beſt ſports of the gain?</p>
                  <p>The reſt of this <hi>Charter</hi> I ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit as aforeſaid, for the reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and ſhall conclude this with the beginning of another, made in Confirmation, Renovation, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuation thereof, by King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in the 28 year of his Reign, as followeth: <hi>viz.</hi> EDWARD <hi>by the Grace of God, King of</hi> England, <hi>Lord of</hi> Ireland, <hi>Duke of</hi> Guyen. <hi>To all Arch-Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>greeting. We have ſeen the great</hi> Charter <hi>of the Lord</hi> Henry <hi>our Father, of the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of</hi> England <hi>in theſe words:</hi> And ſo beginneth the <hi>Charter</hi> as aforeſaid, and ondeth this, and it together, ſaying, <q>We ratifying and approving theſe gifts, and grants aforeſaid, confirm, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111570:27"/>make ſtrong the ſame for us, and our Heirs perpetually, and by tenor of theſe preſents renew the ſame, Willing, and granting for Vs, and Our Heirs, that this Charter, <hi>and all and ſingular its Articles for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, ſhall be ſtedfaſtly, and invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably obſerved; And if any Article in the ſame</hi> Charter <hi>conteined yet hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirto peradventure hath not been obſerved, nor kept; We will, and by Our Authoritie Royal command from henceforth firmly they be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Theſe,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>being witneſſes. Given at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>under Our own hand the</hi> 28 <hi>of</hi> March, <hi>in the</hi> 28 <hi>year of Our Reign.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, where the L. <hi>C.</hi> maintaineth the Statute of <hi>Marlebridge</hi> made 51 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. cap. 5. which ſaith, <hi>The great</hi> Charter <hi>ſhall be obſerved in all its Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, as well in ſuch as pertain to the King, as to others, and that ſhall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of before the Juſtices in Eyre in their Circuits, and before Sheriffs in their Counties when need ſhall be, and writs ſhall be freely granted againſt them that do offend, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fore the King, or the Juſtices of the Bench, or before Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices in Eyre, when they come into thoſe parts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And the offendors when they be convict ſhall be grievouſly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by our ſovereign Lord the King, in form above mentioned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:111570:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>I ſhall but ask, Why not Juſtices in Eyre ſtill? And why not Writs <hi>Gratis</hi> ſent to the Sheriff of every Countie, to enquire of offences, and offendors againſt the great <hi>Charter?</hi> And doth not this Statute prove, that Sheriffs ought to have ſuch Writs, and to make ſuch enquiries? And that the King referred himſelf, as well as others, to the judgements, as well of Juſtices in Eyre, as of the Juſtices of the Bench? and that he would have his Writs granted as well againſt him, as others, and that <hi>Gratis?</hi> doth it not futther prove, that Kings accounted the Juſtices in Eyre, his Juſtices, and their Court, his Court; as well as the <hi>Kings-Bench?</hi> how therefore doth the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> hereafter call them new Juſtices, and their Court, new Court? But more of that in its place.</p>
                  <p>Now having done with ſo much of <hi>Mag. Charta</hi> as I promiſed: and with the 5 Chapter of the Statute of <hi>Marlebridge:</hi> and the 8 of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> Here enſueth the Confirmation of the great <hi>Charter,</hi> made at <hi>London</hi> 10 <hi>Octob. Anno</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. three years before that which
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111570:28"/>is Printed before it, becauſe that containeth all the <hi>Charter</hi> in 38. chapters at large, and this but 7. In the Firſt of which it confirmeth both <hi>Charters,</hi> and every Article thereof; both made 9<hi rend="sup">o</hi>; <hi>H.</hi> 3. in general words, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Edward <hi>by the grace of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 1. <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>King of</hi> England, <hi>Lord of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and Duke of</hi> Guyen. <hi>To all thoſe that theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Letters ſhall hear or ſee, Greet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Know ye, that We to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and of Holy Church, and to the profit of Our Realm, have granted for Vs, and Our Heirs; That the</hi> Charter <hi>of</hi> Liberties, <hi>and the</hi> Charter <hi>of</hi> Forreſts, <hi>which were made by the Commonalty of the Realm, in the time of King</hi> Henry <hi>Our Father, ſhall be kept in every point without breach. And We will, that the ſame</hi> Charter <hi>ſhall be ſent under Our Seal, aſwel to Our Juſtices of the Forreſt, as to others; And to all Sheriffs of Shiers, and to all Our other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and to all Our Cities through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Realm, together with Our Whits, in the which ſhall be contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they cauſe the foreſaid</hi> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>to be publiſhed; And to Declare to the People, that We have confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in all points. And that Our Iuſtices, Sheriffs, Maiors, and other Miniſters, which under Vs, have the Laws of Our Land to guid, ſhall allow the ſame</hi> Charters
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111570:29"/>
                     <hi>pleaded before them in Iudgement, in all their points,: That is to wit; The</hi> Great Charter, <hi>as the Common Law; And the</hi> Charter <hi>of the</hi> Forreſt, <hi>for the Wealth of Our Realm.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Title of this Statute</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) <hi>is</hi> Confirmationes Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum de Libertatibus Angliae &amp; Forreſtae,<note place="margin">L. <hi>C.</hi> upon <hi>Conſ. C.</hi> f. 526.</note> viz. <hi>The Confirmations of the Charters of the Liberties of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, <hi>and of the Forreſt: And true it is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that hereby the ſaid</hi> Charters <hi>are expreſly confirmed; but they are alſo excellently interpreted, (which is a Confirmation in Law) for here is nothing Enacted, but is included within</hi> Magna Charta. <hi>And by the Commonalty</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, by the conſent of all the Realm, by Authority of Parliament: and many times by the Commonalty of</hi> England, <hi>is ſignified an Act of Parliament,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>before Printing, and before the Reign of King</hi> Hen. <hi>the</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, <hi>Statutes were Ingroſſed in Parchment, and by the Kings Writ Proclaimed by the Sheriff of every Countie: this was the ancient Law of</hi> England, <hi>that the Kings Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments iſſued, and were publiſhed in form of Writs (as then it was.) An excellent courſe, and worthie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored,</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:111570:29"/>&amp;c. <hi>This Clauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is worthie to be written in letters of gold,</hi> viz. <hi>That our Juſtices, Sheriffs, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jors, and other Miniſters, which under us have the Laws of the Land to guid them ſhall allow the ſaid</hi> Charters <hi>in all points, which ſhall come before them in Judgement. And here it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, That the Laws are the Judges Guides, or Leaders, according to that old Rule,</hi> Lex eſt Exercitus Judicum, viz. <hi>The Law is the Judges Armie:</hi> Tutiſſimus Doctor, viz. <hi>The ſafeſt Teacher: or</hi> Lex eſt optimus Iudicis Synagogus, viz. <hi>Their beſt Synagoug. And</hi> Lex eſt tutiſſimus caſſis, viz. <hi>Their ſafest Fortreſs. There is an old legal word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>called</hi> Guidagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, viz. <hi>Guidage, which ſignifieth an Office of guiding Travelors through dangerous and unknown ways. Here it appeareth that the Laws of the Realm, hath this Office to guid the Iudges in all cauſes that come before them, in the ways of right Juſtice, who never yet miſguided any man that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainlie knew them, and truly followed them. The ſence of the words, That the great</hi> Charter <hi>is to be holden for the Common Law, is, that it is a Common Law to all, in amendment of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111570:30"/>Realm; that is, of great miſchiefs, and inconveniencies, which oppreſſed the whole Realm, before the making there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>Doth nor the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> by all this his expreſſion, commend this Statute very highly? Why did he not in his duty cauſe it to be obſerved in his time? And had not Iuſtices of the Forreſt, and other Iuſtices, Sheriffs Majors, and other Miniſters of his time (had they received the Great <hi>Charter</hi> with the Kings Writs) power thereby, as well as he, to cauſe the ſaid <hi>Charter</hi> to be publiſhed to the People, and that the King had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it in all points? Why did he (by neglecting his duty to ſend the ſaid <hi>Charter</hi> and Writs unto them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly) make them fail of their duties? Doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs by this clauſe, <hi>Worthie,</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>to be written in letters of gold, That Sheriffs, Majors, and other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, as well as Justices, and other Juſtices as well as thoſe at</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>have, or ought to have the Law of</hi> England <hi>to be their guid, and ought to allow</hi> Magna Charta <hi>in all points, which in any</hi> Plea <hi>ſhall be before them?</hi>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:111570:30"/>Why then do the Iuſtices at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> by their <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> and other Writs, (as aforeſaid)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diſturb, and prevent all Sheriffs, Majors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to exerciſe their Offices, before Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or after, without proof of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, or manifeſt Errors commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them in their Iudgements? Why do not the Iuſtices at <hi>Wiſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> (when they have Perſons, and Cauſes brought before them by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of their Writs) allow <hi>Mag. Car.</hi> to be Pleaded before themſelves, ſince they will ſuffer no others to hear it? How can it be true, (when they do not) that the Law is their guid? Do not they aſſume the ſole Guiding, Learning, Interpreting, Exerciſing, and Over ruling of the Law to themſelves, when they ſuffer no other Iuſtices, or Miniſters of the King, but themſelves to have any Judgement therein, as aforeſaid? Why do they bely the Law ſo much, as to call it their <hi>Guid,</hi> their <hi>Teacher,</hi> their <hi>Army,</hi> their <hi>Synagogue,</hi> their <hi>Fortreſs;</hi> when it is manifeſt, That their Attorneys, their Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, their Catch-polls, and their Goalers, are their <hi>Guids, Teachers, Supernumerous Armies,</hi> and <hi>Invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111570:31"/>Fortreſſes,</hi> (as they truſt, but may be deceived) all whoſe ways are to Injuſtice as aforeſaid? How can that Law be called Common to all, which They, and theſe their Creatures, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolize, Ingroſs, and Appropriate all to themſelves as aforeſaid?</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>And We will,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">C. 2. <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>That if any Indge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be given from henceforth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the points of the</hi> Charters <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, by the Iuſtices, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Our Miniſters, that hold</hi> Plea <hi>before them againſt the points of the</hi> Charters, <hi>it ſhall be undone, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en for nought.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whatſoever Judgement is given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Statute of</hi> Magna Charta,<note place="margin">L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Con. C.</hi> f. 527.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. is made void by this Act, and may be reverſed by a Writ of Error, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Judgement is given against the Law; for this Act ſaith,</hi> Soir de fair &amp; pur nienttenus, viz. <hi>as the Stat. Engliſheth it ſelf,</hi> It ſhall be undone and holden for nought.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>If ſo? Why ſhould not all Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (appearing as aforeſaid, to be contrary to <hi>Mag. Charta</hi>) which are given for Arreſts, and Impriſonment of mens Bodies for Debt, be undone,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111570:31"/>and held for nought? Why did M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Garland</hi> lately trouble the moſt High Court of Parliament (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by ſo doing, he ſhewed himſelf an unworthy Member) with a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous uſeleſs Act of his drawing, for the Enlarging poor Priſoners for Debt? Why did not he, (if he did ever read this place of the Lord <hi>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.)</hi> mind the Parliament to command the Judges (who ſeem, if they have read it, to have forgot it) to reverſe their Erroneous judgements againſt Debtors, ſo far as they extend to their Impriſonment, and to ſend their <hi>Liberate</hi> to all their Goalers, to ſet open all their Goal dores, and let forth ſo many of the Priſoners for Debt, as they have left alive? The poor, becauſe they have no Eſtate whereof to pay; the rich, becauſe they have Eſtates ſufficient for all, or part; againſt which Eſtates, ſo much of their judgements may ſtand, as concerneth that, and not their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: and Executions may be taken thereupon, by <hi>Elegit,</hi> or <hi>Fieri facias,</hi> according to the Statute of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the 2. cap. 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. agreeable to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the Parliament not to be troubled, except to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111570:32"/>the Iudges by an Order, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie their judgements according to that Law which is in force, and ſo forgo their Errors, and Repealed Statute of the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> c. 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. which ought to be no Guid, Leader, or Teacher, to learned and grave Judges, that can never be miſguided by the right law, if (as the Lord <hi>C.</hi> ſaith) <hi>they certainly know it, and be pleaſed truly to follow it.</hi> And by this courſe, as well the Creditors of the rich Debtors, as the poor Priſoners for Debt, (that have been wronged by the Judges Erronious judgements, and proceedings againſt <hi>Mag. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>) may be partly redreſſed, and ſo reſt ſatisfied, until the Parliament be pleaſed to right them further (as ſhall appear hereafter they may.) So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may that Priſoner, (which is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned again after his inlargement by <hi>Garlands</hi> Act) be Enlarged again by the ſame Judge that Committed him, without troubling the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or People with any ſuch Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, as is lately divulged; or ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Apprentices Out-Cry</hi> to run ſo far, That now it will never be ſtopped till the Thieves be taken.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:111570:32"/>
                  <q>
                     <hi>And that all Arch Biſhops,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cap. 4. <hi>Excom.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>and Biſhops, ſhall pronounce the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication againſt all thoſe that by word, deed, or counſel, do contrary to the ſaid</hi> Charters, <hi>or that in any point break, or undo them; And that the ſaid Curſe be twice a year Denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and Publiſhed by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates aforesaid: And if the ſame Prelates, or any of them, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs in the Denunciation of the ſaid Sentences; the Arch-Biſhops of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and</hi> York, <hi>for the time being, ſhall Compel, and Diſtrain them to the Execution of their Duties, in Form afore-ſaid.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Excommunication the Prelates could not pronounce without Warrant by Authoritie of Parliament,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>C.</hi> upon Confir Cart. f. 527.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe it concerned Temporal cauſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>Was not the Authority of this Parliament ſufficient Warrant for Prelates to pronounce Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation according to the Tenor, and limitation of this Act? Doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſay before, <hi>That this Act is not onely an Expreſs Confirmation of</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>but alſo, a Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it in Law?</hi> Doth he not ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that; <hi>That</hi> Magna Charta <hi>ſhould live for ever, and in all Succeſſions of Ages for evermore?</hi> Is not the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111570:33"/>of the Excommunication gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by this Act to the Prelates to pronounce? Had the Prelates any more to do therein, but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce an Excommunication? What meaneth <hi>Ipſo Facto</hi> in the Act, but to let all future Ages under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, That the breach of <hi>Mag. Cha.</hi> which is a Declaration of the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws of <hi>England,</hi> is ſuch an Offence as deſerveth an everlaſting Curſe inflicted by the Law it ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Breakers for ever? Which Curſe receiveth no more ſtrength from the Pronouncer, than a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death from a Iudge, who doth but tell a Fellon whom the Law condemneth, what ſhall be the manner of his Death. If any Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication was ever pronounced by virtue of this Act (as there were two in two ſeveral Kings Reigns) were not thoſe Excommunications in force, and ſo to continue as long as <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelf? the Prelates, and their Succeſſours neglect of their Duties, by diſcontinuing ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciations twice yearly, afterwards notwithſtanding? If ſo? Are not thoſe Excommunications ſtill in force, except Abſolutions be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111570:33"/>granted, and given by equal Authority to that whereby thoſe Excommunications were Denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? If ſo? Are not Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, until Abſolutions, of the ſame accompt, and validity in Law, as Out-lawries, until they be rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? If ſo? Are not all the Lands, Goods, and Chattels of all Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municats, now the States, as formerly they were the Kings, and ſo Seiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Sequeſtrable, and Convertible to that uſe, until Abſolution? And ought not ſatisfaction precede Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution? Ought not that ſatisfaction extend to every particular man that hath been wrong'd in this caſe, which (as the L. <hi>C.</hi> ſaith) <hi>is a Temporal caſe,</hi> and ſo called, in reſpect of the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of all men, called by the Clergy, <hi>Temporal,</hi> for diſtinction from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that would be called <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al?</hi> And ſo (as I believe) not to be commuted by a <hi>Prelatical Sentence,</hi> to a trivial Pennance; nor pardoned by Parliament, without excepting every particular Intereſt. And what Parliament can Pardon, or Abſolve Offendours againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> but by the Rules of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> without offending <hi>Magna Charta</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:111570:34"/>themſelves, and incurring the ſame Excommunication, as they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred that would be Abſolved? If Excommunications be no Terrors to <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> Judges, Juſtices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who neither Believe, nor fear, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, Hell, God, Juſtice, nor Laws, (though they cannot in nature and reaſon, but know that ſuch there are, and are to be beleived, feared, and obeyed) ſhall not Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be ſufficient Warrants for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, Engliſh Chriſtians in <hi>England,</hi> (being warranted not onely, as the L. <hi>C.</hi> ſaith, <hi>By Authority of Parliament,</hi> but of many Parliaments, ſuch Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of ſuch Infallibility as were thoſe wherein <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and all its Confirmations were made, and grounded upon the Common-Laws of <hi>England,</hi> which, as all Lawyers profeſs, were grounded upon the Law of God, the Word of God, the God of Chriſtians, Chriſt Jeſus, the God of Truth, even Truth it ſelf,) to put them in Execution? If not? To what ends are Parliaments, or the Laws of God, and man, to ſuch as dare not, or will not, if, and when they may? Doth not the Statute of <hi>Ano</hi>. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>P. &amp; M.</hi> cap. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:111570:34"/>made it Fellony for twelve Engliſh perſons, or above, to aſſemble toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of purpoſe to break any point of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> imply it to be Warrantable for all the People of <hi>England</hi> to Aſſemble together, to cauſe the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> made by all their conſents, to be obſerved, and to puniſh not onely the Breakers, but alſo the onely begetters, and cauſers of all the Breakers, and Breaches of all the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the onely aſſumers of the knowledg thereof, and concealers of that knowledge from the People; ſo that none but themſelves, can know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly break the Laws, becauſe they will not let them know them? Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, If Excommunications be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing formidable to Lawyers, to make them care whether they incur, or ſhun them, but as their profit guids them? Let us ſee what the L. <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith, fol. 536. concerning the concluſion of this Act, and the Seals that were put to it, and the Oaths of the King and Parliament, then and for ever, for the Ratification of it, omitted in the Stat. at large, in Print, but to be ſeen in the Tower, <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 7<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>no</hi>. 60. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111570:35"/>with the word <hi>Simile,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Note</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Solemnitie of this Act, in that all the Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, Earls, Berons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>did put their Seals thereunto.</hi> A rare example, which was done for the obliging of them the more firmly to the obſervation of this Act, which concerned the Laws, Liberties, and Free-Cuſtoms of their Countrey; and for their greater Obligation for the due Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of this Act, they took a voluntary Corporal Oath.</p>
                  <p>And let us note,<note place="margin">Expoſt &amp; Q.</note> that if the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and this Parliament, hath made the Prelates ſenſible of their ſlighting of their Predeceſſors Excommunications, ſeals and oaths? by what juſtice, or excuſes, ſhall Lawyers avoid the ſame Judgement? And though the Ignorance of <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> and the Law (which Lawyers have begotten &amp; cauſed by conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame from them as aforeſaid) can be no ſafe Plea for any with God, or man, without prayers for Remiſſion, and manifeſtation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; yet is Ignorance a better ſubject for mercy, than knowing wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; and the people, while igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> are more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111570:35"/>of grace for the breaking of it, than when they know it, if they put not the Iudgements of it, in Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, againſt the cauſers of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
                  <p>Now I ſhall let you ſee, that there were two <hi>Excommunications</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt the breakers of <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> according to this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; as followeth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>The Year of our Lord One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred fiftie three,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munic. prim.</note> 
                     <hi>the third of</hi> May, <hi>in the great Hall of the Ring at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>in the preſence, and by the aſſent of the Lord</hi> Henry <hi>by the Grace of God, King of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and the Lord</hi> Richard <hi>Earl of</hi> Cornwall <hi>his brother;</hi> Roger Bigor <hi>Earl of</hi> Norfolk <hi>and</hi> Suffolk, <hi>Marſhal of</hi> England; Humohrey <hi>Earl of</hi> Herford; Henry <hi>Earl of</hi> Oxford; John <hi>Earl</hi> Warren, <hi>and other eſtates of the Realm of</hi> England: <hi>We</hi> Boniface, <hi>by the mercie of God, Arch-biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>Primate of all</hi> England; T. <hi>of</hi> London, H. <hi>of</hi> Ely, S. <hi>of</hi> Worceſter, E. <hi>of</hi> Lincoln, W. <hi>of</hi> Norwich, P. <hi>of</hi> Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, W. <hi>of</hi> Salisbury, W. <hi>of</hi> Durham, R. <hi>of</hi> Exceſter, M. <hi>of</hi> Carlile, W. <hi>of</hi> Bath, E. <hi>of</hi> Rocheſter, T. <hi>of S.</hi> Davids, <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, apparrelled in Pontificals, with tapers burning againſt the breakers of the Churches Liberties, and of the Liberties, or other Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of the Realm of</hi> England, <hi>and namely of thoſe which are contained
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:111570:36"/>in the</hi> Charter <hi>of the Common Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;</hi> Charter <hi>of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; have denounced the ſentence of</hi> Excommunication <hi>in this Form: By the Authoritie of Almightie God, the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt, and of the glorious Mother of God, and perpetual Virgin</hi> Mary; <hi>of the bleſſed Apoſtles</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul; <hi>and of all Apoſtles, and of all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; of bleſſed</hi> Edward <hi>King of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>and of all the Saints of heaven; We Excommunicate, accurſe, and from the benefits of our holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church, we ſequeſter all thoſe that hereafter willingly, and maliciouſly deprive, or ſpoil the Church of her Right; and all thoſe that by any craft, or wilineſs do vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, break, diminiſh, or change the Churches liberties, and Free-cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms contained in the</hi> Charters <hi>of the Common liberties, and of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, granted by our Lord the King to Arch biſhops Biſhops, and other Prelates of</hi> England: <hi>And likewiſe to the Earls, Barons, Knights, and other Freeholders of the Realm; and all that ſecretly or openly, by deed, word, or counſel, do make Statutes, or obſerve them being made, or that bring in Cuſtoms, or keep them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought in, againſt the ſaid li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertis, or any of them, the Writers, Lawmakers. Counſellors, and the Executors of them, and all thoſe that ſhall preſume to Judge againſt them. All and every which Perſons before mentioned, that willingly
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:111570:36"/>ſhall commit any thing of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, let them well know; That they incur the foreſaid ſentence</hi> Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſacto, <hi>firſt upon the deed done. And thoſe that commit ought ignorantly, and be admoniſhed, except they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves within</hi> 15. <hi>daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time of the Admonition; and make full ſatisfaction for that they have done, at the will of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, ſhall be from that time forth, wrapped in the ſame ſentence. And with the ſame ſentence, we burthen all thoſe that preſume to perturb the peace of our Sovereign Lord the King, and of the Realm. To the perpetual memory of which thing, We the aforeſaid Prelates have put Our Seals to theſe Preſents.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>What though the Form of this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication</hi> be Popiſh?<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> Is not the Subſtance the maintenance of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Liberties? And is not that all which the meaning of this Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth? If Judges and Prelates, as well ſince King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. as before, have neglected their Duties in Itte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the charge of their Functions, the firſt, in pronoucing Sentence, and the other in Executing it; doth not once pronoucing, &amp; once exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of ſuch one Sentence of Law, as concerneth all Ages, Sexes, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111570:37"/>Conditions of People to learn and remember, no leſs for the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their lives, and livelihoods, than Scriptures for their Salvation, take away the plea of Ignorance from all men? Shall any man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that ſin which he knoweth to be once ſo Declared by the Law, and think to avoid puniſhment becauſe not often ſo Declared by Law-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours? Are not all men bound to ſearch the Scriptures, and learn the Laws at their perils therefore? If Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance were a plea, ſhall knowledge be excuſed? Profeſſors of knowledg? nay, ſuch as ingroſs that Profeſſion from all others, nay more, ſuch as are the onely cauſers and puniſhers of all other mens Ignorance?</p>
                  <p>It appeareth that this Sentence was Denounced in the time of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Now followeth another, Denounced upon the ſaid Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made in the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. year of King <hi>8d.</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>In the Name of the Father,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Excom.</hi> 2.</note> 
                     <hi>the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Amen, <hi>Whereas our Sovereign Lord the King, to the Honour of God, and Holy Church, and for the common
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:111570:37"/>profit of the Realm, hath granted for him and his Heirs for ever, theſe Articles above written.</hi> Robert <hi>Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Cauterbury, <hi>Primate of all</hi> England, <hi>Admoniſhed all his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, Once, Twice, and Thrice. Becauſe that ſhortneſs will not ſuffer ſo much delay, as to give knowledge to all the People of</hi> England <hi>of theſe Preſents in Writing: We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore injoyn all perſons of what E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ſoever they be, that they, and every of them, as much as in them is, ſhall uphold and maintain theſe Articles, granted by our Sovereign Lord the King, in all points; And all thoſe that in any point do reſiſt, or break, or in any manner hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter procure, counſel, or any wiſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to reſiſt, or break thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or go about it by word, or deed; openly, or privily, by any manner of pretence, or colour: We the foreſaid Arch-Biſhop by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in this Writing expreſſed, do</hi> Excommunicate, and accurſe, and from the Lord Jeſu Chriſt, and from all the company of Heaven, and from all all the Sacraments of Holy Church, do ſequeſter, and exclude.</q>
                  <p>Doth not the word, <hi>Hereafter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt &amp; Q. 1</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to all ſucceſſions, and implie a Duration, as long as there be a <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> and a breaker of it? Do not Parliamentarie Oaths, as well as their Laws, include abſents, and futures,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:111570:38"/>as well as preſent? If neither Oaths, nor Excommunications be obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to Atheiſts, ſhall not their hands, and ſeals, bind them and their Heirs, and Executors after them, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bonds ſigned and ſealed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween private parties, commonly do? And more ſpecially, ſuch as take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the ſole Execution, and Adminiſtration of the Laws, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Freehold of <hi>England?</hi> Shall not <hi>Charters</hi> of Parliament, made, ſigned, ſealed, and confirmed by Authoritie of Parliaments, bind all Subjects, their Heirs, Executors, and Adminiſtrators, as well, and as far, as private <hi>Charters</hi> of Feofments ſhall bind their Contractors, and their Heirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay, as far as Acts of Parliament can bind, till repealed? Is not every Court called <hi>Curia,</hi> of the Care it ought to have to execute that charge it undertaketh? and not to exact, and raiſe Fees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging themſelves of all their ſaid Obligations to do even Juſtice to all men, and to force men to pay thoſe exactions, even for doing injuſtice? If all before written be not ſufficient to diſcover that to be true, and that therefore the Lives,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:111570:38"/>Lands, &amp; Goods, poſſeſſed by Judges, Lawyers, all, or moſt of them, are in the States power to ſeize into their hands, to the uſe of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as aforeſaid; let us look a little further, and we ſhall find more that may. And firſt, the Statute cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Articuli ſuper Chartas,</hi> viz.<note place="margin">Stat. of Artic. on the great <hi>Chart. A.</hi> 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.</note> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles upon the great Charters, made 28. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>viz.</hi> the ſame year as the Confirmation at large (which conſiſteth of 38. chapters of <hi>Magna Charta</hi>) was made; proveth further, as followeth.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>For as much as the Articles of the great Chart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r <hi>of the Liberties of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,<note place="margin">Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> 
                        <hi>and of the</hi> Charter <hi>of the Forreſt, the which King</hi> Henry, <hi>Father to our Sovereing Lord the King, granted to his People for the Weal of his Realm, have not been heretofore ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ne kept, and all becauſe there was no puniſhment executed upon them which offended againſt the points of the</hi> Charters <hi>before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned: Our Sovereign Lord the King hath again granted, revived, &amp; confirmed them at the requeſts of his Prelates, Earls, &amp; Barons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in His Parliament holden at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>in the</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8 <hi>year of his reign. And hath ordained, enacted, and eſtabliſhed certain Articles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all them that offend contrary to the points of the ſaid</hi> Charters, <hi>or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:111570:39"/>any part of them, or that in any wiſt tranſgreſs them, in the form that enſueth,</hi> viz.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt of all, That from henceforth the great</hi> Charter <hi>of the Liberties of</hi> England, <hi>granted to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie of the Realm, and the</hi> Charter <hi>of Forreſt in like manner granted, ſhall be obſerved, kept, &amp; maintained in every point, in as am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wiſe, as the King hath granted, renued, and confirmed them by this</hi> Chart. <hi>And that the</hi> Charter <hi>be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to every Sheriff of</hi> England <hi>under the Kings Seal, to be read four times in the year before the people in the full County, that is to wit, the next County day after the Feaſt of</hi> S. Michael, <hi>and the next County day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Feaſt of the</hi> Circumciſion, <hi>and after</hi> Eaſter, <hi>and after the Feaſt of</hi> S. John Baptiſt. <hi>And for theſe two</hi> Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>to be firmly obſerved in every point, and Article (where before no remedy was at the Common Law) there ſhall be choſen in every Shire Court by the Commonaltie of the ſame ſhire, three ſubſtantial men, Knights,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Oyer</hi> &amp; <hi>Term.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>or other lawfull, wiſe, and well diſpoſed Perſons to be Iuſtices, which ſhall be aſſigned by the Kings Letters Patents under the great Seal, to hear, and determine (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other Writ but onely their Commiſſion) ſuch plaints as ſhall be made upon all thoſe that commit, or offend againſt any point contained in the aforeſaid</hi> Charters, <hi>in the Shires where they be aſſigned, as well
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:111570:39"/>in Franchiſes, as without, and as well for the Kings ſervants out of their places, as for other. And to hear the plaints from day to day without any delay, and to determine them without allowing the delays which be at the Common Law: And the ſame Knights ſhall have power to puniſh all ſuch as ſhal be attainted of any Treſpaſs done contrary to any point of the two ſaid</hi> Charters <hi>(where no remedy was before at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, as before is ſaid) by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, or by Fine, or by Amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciament, according to the Treſpaſs. Nevertheleſs the King, nor none of his Councel that made this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, intend that by virtue hereof, any of the foreſaid Knights ſhall hold any manner of Plea by power, for to admit any ſuit in ſuch caſes wherein there hath been remedy provided in times paſſed, after the courſe of the Common Law by writ. Nor alſo that the Common Law ſhould be prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, nor the</hi> Ch. <hi>aforeſaid, in any point. And the K. Willeth, that if all three be not preſent, or cannot at all times attend to do their Office in form a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, the King commandeth that two of them ſhall do it. And it is Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that the Kings Sheriffs, and Bailiffs ſhall be attendant to do the commandments of the foreſaid Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, as far forth as appertaineth unto their Offices. And beſides theſe things granted upon the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the</hi> Charters aforeſaid. The King of his ſpecial Grace for redreſs
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:111570:40"/>of the grievances that the people hath ſuſtained by reaſon of his Wars, and for the amendment of their Eſtate, &amp; to the intern that they may be the more ready to do him ſervice, and the more willing to aſsiſt, and aid him in time of need; hath granted certain Articles, the which he ſuppoſeth ſhall not onely be obſerved of his leige. people, but alſo ſhall be as much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, or more, than of the Articles heretofore granted.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One of the cauſes for the making this Act,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>Coke</hi> f. 537, 538, 539.</note> 
                     <hi>was</hi> (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> as in the Preamble is ſuggeſted) <hi>that there was no certain puniſhment in many points eſtabliſhed by the ſaid</hi> Charters <hi>against the violators of the ſame; which alſo by this Act</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is remedied: And the word,</hi> People, <hi>here</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth include all the Kings Subjects,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And again, the word,</hi> Pain ne fuit eſtable, <hi>ſome read</hi> (ſaith he) Pain ne fuit execute, <hi>and that is true in effect; but the Original, is,</hi> Pain ne fuit eſtable; <hi>that is, no pain was ſet down certain: And</hi> (ſaith he, fol. 539.) <hi>This Act had but the force of a</hi> Charter, <hi>until confirmed by this Parliament, the</hi> 34<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Ed. 1. <hi>And that theſe</hi> Charters <hi>ſhould be read four times in the year, in full County, here is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:111570:40"/>an order taken for the publiſhing. And</hi> Ou remedie ne fuit avant, <hi>&amp;c. is to be conſtrued</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>where no Action was given by the Kings Writ, to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued at Common Law,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Again, here</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for the better Execution of thoſe glorious two Lights,</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>and</hi> Charta Foreſtae, <hi>a new Court, and new Juſtices were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Again</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>theſe clauſes againſt the Kings Servants out of their places, as well as others: And to hear the Plaints without delay, day by day, and to determine them without admitting ſuch delaies as be at Common Law, was the firſt ground of the raiſing of the Juſtices called,</hi> Trail Baſton, <hi>and their Courts ſo called, in respect of their precipitate proceedings from day to day, without ſuch convenient leiſure and time, as Common Law allowed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they in the end had ſuch Authoritie, as Juſtices in Eyer; but albeit they had their Authoritie by Act of Parliament, yet if they erred in judgement, a Writ of Error did lie by the general Rule of the Common Law, to reverſe the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the</hi> Kings-Bench; <hi>which being once reſolved, and known, and their Juriſdiction fettered with ſo many li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations, their Authoritie, by little and little vaniſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:111570:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>Was there any certain Pain eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by this Statute, againſt the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> other than by Commiſſion in Eyer, that the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices might determine, and puniſh the Offendors by Impriſonments, Fines or Amerciaments, according to the Treſpaſs? Ought not the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> to have ſo puniſhed all ſuch as were Indicted before Sheriffs, or Juſtices in Eyer, who had power to inquire, and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them of all ſuch Offendors, and Offences againſt <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> by the Statute of <hi>Marlebridge?</hi> 51. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>? Doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſay elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>That all Statutes ought to be conſtrued ſo, as that there ſhould be no failer of Juſtice:</hi> ſhould not the Juſtices of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued <hi>Magna Charta</hi> ſo? Doth not the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chap. of <hi>Mag. Charta</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly direct; <hi>That all offendors ought to be Amercied by their equals, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the quantitie of the Trespaſs?</hi> Doth the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſpeak truth, when he ſaith, <hi>this Statute gave any man Remedie for the certaintie of the puniſhment, other than</hi> Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <hi>did before?</hi> Was it not made more uncertain by referring it to the Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:111570:41"/>in Eyers diſcretion, whether A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciaments, Fyne, or Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Doth he not confeſs plainly, (when he ſaith, <hi>It is true in effect, that the Pain was not Executed, as ſome read, inſtead of the Pain was not Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,</hi>) That it was the fault of the Juſtices of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> in not Executing the Pain of Amercying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as they might, and ought to have done) was the cauſe of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wering the Juſtices in Eyer, (who were but Enquirers before) now to determine, and puniſh ſuch Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and Offences, as they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, <hi>viz.</hi> The Kings Servants, with whom by this time, they of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> tampered for their Offices? And was it not for the ſame cauſe, the people were Declared to be chooſers of Juſtices in Eyer? And doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſhew a great ſpight between himſelf, and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; whom he would have to be ancient; and the Juſtices in Eyer, whom he calleth a new Court, and new Juſtices? And ſhew his Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be weak, as his Envy was ſtrong, when he is forced to give himſelf the Lye, (either here, or in his Expoſition of the Stat. of <hi>Marle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:111570:42"/>where he ſaith; <hi>They were then Juſtices, and a court, though but for Inquirie? And upon the</hi> 23<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>Chap. of</hi> Magna Charta; he ſaith, they uſed before that time to give charge to all Juries concerning Wears <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſay, fol. 235. <hi>That</hi> Bracton <hi>wrote before the making</hi> Weſt. 1. <hi>which was</hi> 3. Ed. 1? And doth not <hi>Bracton</hi> lib. 3. cap. 11, 12, and 13. ſay, <hi>Juſtices in Eyer were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his time?</hi> Doth not <hi>Camden</hi> in his <hi>Britannia,</hi> pag. 104. ſay, <hi>They were Inſtituted by King</hi> Hen. 2? Doth not <hi>Hoveden</hi> in his <hi>Annais, part, poſter.</hi> fol. 113. b. confirm the ſame? And add that K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. divided the Realm in ſix parts, &amp; ſetled thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices in Eyer to every part, whoſe names he relateth? And doth not the <hi>Mirror of Juſtice</hi> lib. 3<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Tit. 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. <hi>Juſtice in Eyer, declare their power at large?</hi> And as for their Election by the people, doth he not ſay, fol. 538. <hi>That</hi> Magna charta, <hi>&amp;c. containeth the ſubſtance of all that is contained in theſe Articles?</hi> And doth he not ſay in his Preamble, <hi>That</hi> Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <hi>is an Act declarative of the ancient Laws, and Cuſtoms of</hi> England <hi>before it, and no introductive of any new?</hi>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:111570:42"/>And fol. 558. <hi>That of ancient time, before the making of this Act, all ſuch Officers, or Ministers, as were inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, either for Preſervation of the Peace of the County, or for execution of Juſtice (becauſe it concerned all the Subjects of that County, and they had a great intereſt in the due and just exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their places) were by force of the Kings Writs in every ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, choſen in full and open County, by the Free-holders of the ſame County?</hi> Again, (ſaith he,) <hi>So it was then, and yet is, of Coroners, and ſo it was then, and yet is, of Knights of the Shire for Parliaments; and of the Verdors of a Foreſt, and likewiſe it was of ancient time of the Sheriff of the County, and reſtored by this Act:</hi> but this is alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by divers Acts of Parliament. Now were not Juſtices in Eyer therefore that were before <hi>Magna Charta</hi> choſen by the peole, as they were Miniſters of Juſtice, wherein the people were concerned? And were they by this Act but reſtored to their ancient juriſdiction, as (the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſaith) Sheriffs were? Was not that alteration which was made by divers Acts of Parliament, made by ſuch Acts as were contrary to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:111570:43"/>
                     <hi>Magna Charta?</hi> And are not, or ought not all ſuch Acts to be void, (as the L. <hi>Coke</hi> hath elſewhere ſaid?) Doth not theſe contradictions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> to have been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted with ſpight and envy againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtices in Eyer? And where in this leaf, he would perſwade the people to ſuſpect Juſtices in Eyer, of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Monopolizing juſtice to wrong the people that chuſe them; can the people believe that theſe Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices (who are to be choſen by them, and to be diſplaced by them, when, and as often as they ſee cauſe) will, or can wrong them more, than thoſe choſen by the King and his Servants, without their conſents, unleſs they can believe that they may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to give their conſents to wrong themſelves? Is it not a Bull of leſs formality than ever any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Bull was, (keeping a man off with his Horns, That he ſhall have no hold of his tail) when he ſaith, <hi>That the clauſe, where no remedy was before,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ought to be expounded, where no Action was given by the Kings Writs, to be purſued at Common Law?</hi> Since by the Statute of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebridge,</hi> Juſtices in Eyer were to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:111570:43"/>inquire by the Kings Writs; and now are, by expreſs words of this chapter, not onely to inquire, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to determine by virtue of their Commiſſions, without the Kings Writs? And what cauſe could they, or can any other Court determine by virtue of their Commiſſion, without the Kings Writs, but is Actionable by the Kings Writs? What doth this Statute give by virtue of this Commiſſion, if all things Actionable by Writs, be not determinable by theſe Commiſſions, without Writs? And what doth this Statute avail, if not conſtructable as others, ſo that there ſhould be no failer of juſtice? Where was the failer of juſtice, but in the Kings Courts, and Iudges, in not executing juſtice upon the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors of <hi>Magna Charta?</hi> Doth it not therefore appear that the ſaid clauſe <hi>(Where no Remedy was before)</hi> ought to be expounded, where no remedy was given before by Iuſtices in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> againſt the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and themſelves, that were the greateſt contractors in the breaches of <hi>Magna Charta?</hi> Were not the Iuſtices in Eyer therefore inabled with a power to ſupply their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:111570:44"/>faults, and to do right to the People, againſt the King himſelf, and all his Servants at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that wilfully failed in their juſtice and power? And where he ſaith; <hi>The Juſtices called,</hi> Trail Baſton, <hi>had like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie as Juſtices in eyer, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Errors, &amp; upon pretence thereof, had all their proceedings transported to the</hi> Kings-Bench; doth it not appear by the Statute called, <hi>Ragman,</hi> that thoſe Iuſtices were made by the King, without the conſent of the people, and ſent abroad (perhaps of purpoſe) to err and abuſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to give colour to the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> to ſend their Writs of Error, for the proceedings of the Iuſtices in Eyer (upon pretence of like Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) ſo to ſuppreſs all Iuſtice againſt themſelves, and their Creatures? Doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> here withal prefer the chargeable delaies of cauſes (ſpun out by Termes, and Years,) before ſpeedy juſtice done day by day, at mens own doors, which he calleth, <hi>Piecipitat?</hi> Doth he not ground this courſe, for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing ſpeedy juſtice by Writs of Errors, upon the reſolution of the Iudges at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which he al
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:111570:44"/>leadgeth as ſufficient to maiſter Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority given by Act of Parliament? And is it not the reſolution of all Lawyers, that no power but Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is equal to Parliament, and no Parliament to be ſo impowred as to croſs <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and its Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations? Doth he not further (ſol. 559.) alleadge the reſolution of all the Iudges of <hi>England,</hi> againſt the King and his Councel, for an Errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Act, when they had choſen a Sheriff for <hi>Lincoln</hi> in a caſe of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without the conſent of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? But to haſten this Treatiſe to an end, I ſhall end this Statute for this time, with few chapters follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>The King hath granted unto his people,<note place="margin">Cap. 8. Elect. of She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifts.</note> that they ſhall have Election of their Sheriff in every Shire (where the Sheriffalty is not of the Fee) if they liſt.</q>
                  <p>I ſhall ſay no more to this, than hath been ſaid before.</p>
                  <q>In ſummons and Attachements in Plea of land,<note place="margin">C. 25. Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons &amp; A. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ach.</note> 
                     <hi>the Whits from henceforth ſhall contain</hi> 15. days full at the leaſt, after the Common Law, if it be not in Attachement of Aſsizes
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:111570:45"/>taken in the Kings preſence, or of Pleas before Iuſtices in Eyer, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Eyer.</q>
                  <p>Upon this I muſt ask,<note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note> Is not a Writ of Debt, Summons? Should not that be given to the party which ought to be ſummoned? Should not an Attachement follow by diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of 15. days, as this Statute pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth? Shall the repealed Statute of the 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>, ſerve Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers turns to make a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Plea real, and Perſonal? And ſhall that Writ of Summons be counterfeited, either in it ſelf, or in its return, as aforeſaid.</p>
                  <q>Such Executions ſhall be done of them that make falſe Returns of Writs,<note place="margin">Ca. 16. Falſe Retur. of Wr.</note> (whereby right is deferred) as it is ordained in the 2. Statute of Weſtminſter, with like pain, at the Kings commandment.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is an Act of Confirmation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">L. <hi>C.</hi> upon Ca. 16, f. 568.</note> 
                     <hi>whereby the Statute of</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>the</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. cap. 39<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>touching falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, is confirmed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Doth not the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Statute of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> cap. 39. ſay,<note place="margin">Expoſt &amp; Q.</note> 
                     <hi>That the King hath commanded that Sheriffs ſhall be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:111570:45"/>puniſhed by the Juſtices once or twice if need be for ſuch falſe Returns? and if they offend a third time, none ſhall have to do therewith but the King,</hi> &amp;c? Doth not the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> aſſume the King to be always there in Perſon? And what they ſpeak, to be his own ſpeech? Is it not they therefore that ſhould puniſh Sheriffs for their falſe Returns, the third time of their offence? But is it not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they, and their Creatures, as well as thoſe of the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> do make falſe Returns in the names of the Sheriffs of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndon,</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi> and do conſequently make thoſe Sheriffs liable to Actions, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid? How can they puniſh thoſe Sheriffs for thoſe falſe Returns, which they themſelves ſuffer their Clerks to make, unknown to the Sheriffs, as aforeſaid? And who but they cauſe, or ſuffer all Sheriffs falſly to Return Exigents with the words, <hi>Per judicium Coronatorum,</hi> and the Coroners names, who know no ſuch thing? And if any man be Out-lawed without the judgement of the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his County, or any mention made thereof in the Sheriffs Return, is not that Outlawry as injurious to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:111570:46"/>the Party, Perjurious in the Judges who admit ſuch a Return, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon it, and as Illegal in the Sheriff that makes ſuch a Return, and as different from due Proces of Law, as the other? And do not thoſe falſe Returns filed upon their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, make all their proceedings thereupon, falſe, and faint Actions as aforeſaid? And if all before writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten be not ſufficient to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the world, that they are not onely Forgers, Perjurers, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema's themſelves, but alſo the onely cauſers of all others to be, or be accompted the like? And that their Lives, Lands, and Goods, are in the immediate diſpoſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State, by the judgements and confeſſions of their own mouths? Behold their Oath, which they vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily take when they aſſume their places, whereby they binde themſelves further, before God, and man, as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>Ye ſhall Swear,<note place="margin">The Oath of the Kings Judges</note> that well and lawfully ye ſhall ſerve our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lord the King, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the office of Iuſtice, and that lawfully ye ſhall Counſel the King in his buſineſs, and that ye ſhall not
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:111570:46"/>councel, nor aſſent to any thing which may turn him to dammage, or diſheriſon, by any manner way, or colour. And that Ye ſhall not know the dammage, or diſheriſon of him, whereof Ye ſhall not do him to be warned by Your ſelf, or by other. And that Ye ſhall do even Law, and Execution of right to all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, rich, and poor, without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving regard to any perſon. And that You take not by Your ſelf, or by other, privily, nor apertly, gift, nor reward of gold, not ſilver, nor of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing which may turn to Your profit unleſs it be meat, or drink, and of ſmall valure, of any man that ſhall have any Plea, or Proces, hanging before You, as long as the Proces ſhall be ſo hanging, nor after the ſame cauſe. And that Ye take no Fee, as long as Ye ſhall be Iuſtice, nor Robes of any may, great or ſmall, but of the King himſelf. And that Ye give none adviſe, nor Counſel to no man, great nor ſmall, in no caſe where the King is party. And in caſe that any of what Eſtatt or Condition they be, come before You in Your Seſsions with Force, and Arms, or other ways againſt the Peace, or againſt the form of the Statute thereof made, to diſturb Execution of the Common Law, or to manace the people that they may not purſue the Law, that Ye do their Bodies to be Arreſted, and put in priſon: and in caſe they be ſuch, that Ye may not Arreſt them, that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:111570:47"/>Ye certifie the King of their names, and of their Miſpriſion haſtily, ſo that he may thereof ordain a coven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able remedie: And that You by Your ſelfe, nor by other, privily, nor apertly, maintain any Plea, or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, hanging in the Kings Court, or elſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where in the Countrie: And that Ye denie to no man common right by the Kings Letters, nor none other mans, nor for none other cauſe; and in caſe any Letters come to You, contrarie to the Law, that You do nothing by ſuch lett, but certifie the King thereof, and go forth to do the Law, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame Letters. And that Ye ſhall do, and procure the profit of the King, and of his Crown, with all things where Ye may reaſonably do the ſame. And in caſe Ye be from henceforth found in default in any of the points aforeſaid; Ye ſhall be at the Kings Will, of Body, Lands, &amp; Goods, thereof to be done as ſhall pleaſe him: As God You help, and all Saints. Anno, 18. <hi>Edward, 3.</hi> Stat. 3.</q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>If Atheiſts can perſwade Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that this Oath was no binding for them that had taken it, (even the Wiſe, Learned, Reverend, Judges, Sages, Scientiſſimous Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi>) ſufficient to keep them within the compaſs of their Oath, Law, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:111570:47"/>Knowledges? Shall not Chriſtians perſwade themſelves, that it is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Confeſſion, Declaration, and judgement of their own mouths that made it, that their forfeitures, <hi>viz.</hi> their Lives, Lands, and Goods, in caſe of their breach of any point of this Oath, are now immediately in the power of the State to diſpoſe of to the publique uſe, at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, without any further Proces, or proceedings in Law, but onely to give Order, and Warrant to Arreſt the perſons of ſuch Offendors to ſtand to their cenſures; and to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſter their Eſtates, and to divide them to the ſaid uſe, accordingly? Did Lords ever uſe any more Law than their own Wills, when they Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred, and puniſhed their villains? Had Lords any more Law, Right, or Reaſon, to Sequeſter, and puniſh their villains at their own Wills, but for that their villains did take their Lands upon conditions to do thoſe ſervices which they and their Lords agreed upon, and gave their Lords their Oaths (as their greateſt bonds) to perform thoſe conditions, or in caſe of breach, to ſuffer their Lords to repoſſeſs their Lands, with the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:111570:48"/>forfeitures of their Goods, (which they gained) and their Lives (which they ſuſtained) upon the ſame? Was the Oath of a Villain (though made by Parliament, to the end that Lords ſhould be well ſerved by their Slaves in their private and meaneſt Offices) of as conſiderable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to be obſerved, or in default thereof, their forfeitures to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, as the Oath of Judges, made and Confirmed by ſeveral Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to the end, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth ſhould be well ſerved by their Juſtices in their publike, and moſt honourable (if rightly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) Offices of Judicature, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice? Are not ſuch Villains, as dare incroach, not onely upon their Lords Lands, and Eſtates, but alſo upon their Lives, and Liberties, dangerous, tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Hyper-Prelatical Uſurpers? Are not ſuch Uſurpers intollerable miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs in a Common-wealth? Who being ſworn ſervants to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth (as by this Oath it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth the Kings Juſtices were) make all the Common-wealth their ſervants, to attend their Trains at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> at their pleaſures? And
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:111570:48"/>all Priſoners for Debt, not onely their own Villains, but alſo Villains to their Villainous Goalors, and Slaves to their Slaves? Are not the meaneſt of the Free-People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> intereſſed in the due executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Juſtice, to which theſe Judges were ſworn? (as well to them, as to Kings) and conſequently ought they not to be ſuch Lords as dare, and will take the forfeitures of ſuch Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, as do them daily Injuſtice? Is not this Oath a ſufficient Evidence in it ſelf, that the takers of it, have, &amp; do dayly break it? &amp; cauſe all others that have, or do break it, to do ſo likewiſe? Since Kings and People have wholly referred themſelves, and their Eſtates, not onely to the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of their Judges, but alſo to their fatherly advertiſements, and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions (whereby they ought not to ſuffer any that depend upon them, to err through ignorance) and they (contrariwiſe) admoniſh none not to offend, but ſuffer, and cauſe more to offend than willingly, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly would; and ſo do, for want of ſuch admonitions, much more increaſe, and enhance the Markets of their Juſtice, by ſuffering no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:111570:49"/>Judges to admoniſh, or Juſtifie any offendors at home, and ingroſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all to themſelves at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or before ſuch as they ſend to frip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for them, in Aſſizes, Goal-Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, and <hi>Niſi priuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</hi> Have not ſome preſent Grafts of the old ſtock Judges of Aſſizes in poſſibility for the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey</hi>) &amp; their Agents in <hi>Chancery,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured ſeveral late Injunctions to be diſſolved in <hi>Chancery,</hi> without the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of both parties whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, to the end onely to beget work for them in the Aſſizes, leſt they ſhould want better? Did our late Judges lawfully counſel King <hi>Charls</hi> in his buſines, when they gave their Reſolutions for him concerning the Ship-money? Did they not aſſent to a thing, or things, that turned to his dammage and diſheriſon, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him, and his Poſterity out of three Kingdoms, and his life to boot, when they aſſented to Ship money, and Monopolies? Did not the Kings Councel and other Serjeants, and Lawyers, draw (if not plot) all ſuch Patents? Got they not more by their Fees, for their adviſe therein, (which were preſent pay) than the King did by his reſervations for intereſt in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:111570:49"/>thoſe Grants which are yet in Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear? Was any thing reſerved to the King thereby, but what his Councel learned thought fit, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him to take, and the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ntees to give? Did not thoſe Judges, that had the keeping of both the Kings Seals, aſſent to all thoſe unlawfull things, whatſoever they Sealed? Briefly, doth not this Oath in every point evidence the Judges at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and their brethren to have been the chief betrayers of Kings and People in their chief truſt, to guide and hold both in the right way, and did they not lead both wrong? And thereby are the chief Authors of all the blood ſpilt, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ruined in theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, in and by theſe late Wars, which were undertaken for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, onely of ſuch deformities in Law, and Government, which (you ſee) they had power to keep in form by their lawfull judgements, or admonitions to the right, or not conſenting to the wrong? Do not our Records, and Hiſtory teſtifie, that all the Civil Wars of <hi>England,</hi> were alwaies undertaken for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Injuſtice, evil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:111570:50"/>and corrupt Lawyers that were alwaies the cauſers thereof, by breaking, and cauſing to be broken the Liberties of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which the People ſought alwaies to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? Were not <hi>Hugh D'Burgo,</hi> Chief Juſtice of <hi>England, Walter D'Lancton,</hi> Lord Treaſurer of <hi>England, Brember, Triſilian, Bellknap, Thorp,</hi> &amp;c. exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of their times in that caſe? If ſo few examples will not ſerve to make all Judges mend, ſhould not all ſuch Judges be made examples, to ſerve poſterity to ſee that ſuch evils are not neceſſary for Common-wealths? Shall ſuch Extrajudical Judges, ſuch lawleſs Lawyers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as will not be tied by Oaths, made in, and by Parliaments; Excommunications denounced by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; <hi>Charters</hi> Signed, Sealed, and Confirmed in, and by Parliaments; nor by Acts, Laws, and Statutes made by full and free Parliaments; be ſuffered to ſit with Chriſtians in Parliaments to make Laws, Votes, Oaths, and other Obligations upon Chriſtians, which ſhall be none to themſelves? But let us ſee further, what an other Act of Parliament ſaith to this Oath, as enſueth, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:111570:50"/>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">The Statut. 20. <hi>E.</hi> 3. Pream. Letter. Juſtice.</note>Edward <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>To the Sheriff of</hi> Stanford, <hi>greeting. Becauſe that by divers complaints made to Vs, We have perceived that the Law of the Land, which We by Our Oath are bound to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, is the leſs well kept, and the execution of the ſame diſturbed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, by maintenance, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement, as well in the Court, as in the Countrey: We greatly moved of Conſcience in this matter, and for this cauſe, deſiring as much for the pleaſure of God, and eaſe, and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs of Our Subjects, as to ſave Our Conſcience, and for to ſave and keep Our ſaid Oath, by the aſſent of the Great men, and other Wiſe men of Our Councel: We have ordein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe things following,</hi> viz.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Cap. 1.</note> 
                        <hi>We have commanded all Our Iuſtices, that they ſhall from henceforth, do even Law, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of right to all our Subjects rich &amp; poor, without having regard to any perſon, and without letting to do right for any letters, or command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which may come to them from Vs, or from any other, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe. And in that any letters,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Letters.</note> writs, or commandments come to the Iuſtices, or to other, deputed to do Law and right, according to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the Realm, in diſturbance of the Law, or of the execution of the ſame, or of right to the parties; the Iuſtices, and other aforeſaid ſhall
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:111570:51"/>proceed, and hold their Courts, and Proceſſes where the Pleas, and matters be depending before them, as if no ſuch Letters, Writs, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments were come to them. And they ſhall certifie Vs, &amp; Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of ſuch commandments as be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the Law, (as before is ſaid) And to the intent that our Iuſtices ſhould do even right to all people,<note place="margin">Juſtice</note> in the manner aforeſaid, without more favour ſhewing to one, more than to another, We have done Our ſaid Iuſtices to be ſworn, that they ſhall not from henceforth, as long as they ſhall be in office of Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Fees. Roabs</note> take Fee nor Roabe of any man, but of Our ſelf. And they ſhall take no gift, nor reward by themſelfs, nor by other, privily, nor apertly of any man that hath to do before them, by any way, except meat and drink, and that of ſmall valure; and that they ſhall give no counſel to a great man, nor ſmall, in caſe where We be Partie, or which do, or may touch Vs in any point, upon pain to be at Our will, Bodie, Lands, and Goods, to do thereof as ſhall pleaſe us, in caſe they do contrarie: And for this cauſe We have increaſed the Fees of the ſame our Iuſtices, in ſuch manner, that it ought reaſonably to ſuffice them.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Expoſt and Quer.</note>Doth not the King ſay here, He is bound by his Oath to maintain the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:111570:51"/>Laws of the Land? Doth not the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> ſay before, <hi>That a King in his Politick capacitie cannot dye?</hi> Did not, or ought not all Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> take the like Oath as this King did? Were they not therefore bound to maintain the Laws of <hi>England</hi> as well as he? and to be adviſed, and ruled by their Judges, how to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them? as the Oath of the Judges, this Statute, and others, do manifeſt they were? Are not Judges as Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal as Kings in their Politick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity? Are they not bound by their Oaths, not onely to maintain, and execute the Laws of <hi>England</hi> againſt all men, without regard of Perſons, but alſo to adviſe their Kings to maintain them, and how ſo to do, and to hinder, or not conſent with their Kings to break them? Were not the maintenances (whereof the King here complaineth, and the procurements as well in Court, as in Countrey, whereby (he ſaith) <hi>the Laws, and the due execution thereof were diſturbed</hi>) the remainders of the Factions of the <hi>Spencers,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who in <hi>Edward</hi> the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. his time had made ſuch Judges, as had put all Laws out of all order; ſo
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:111570:52"/>that this King, being <hi>Edward</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. could not reform what had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed hitherto? but now endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth to do it by means of this Oath made in Parliament in the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. year of his Reign, and this Act made in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. If Kings en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to perform their duties (as this King did, and Judges would not) ſhould not ſuch Judges ſuffer, as in this Kings time divers did? If Kings, and Judges, (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their Oaths, and Offices) omit their duties (as this Kings Father, and his Judges did) ſhould not ſuch Kings and Judges ſuffer for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults, as he and they did? If Kings, and Biſhops did lately neglect their duties, (contrary to their Oaths, and Offices) and were puniſhed for their defaults? why not ſuch Judges as were the greater Delinquents for ſuffering them ſo to offend? and more for conſenting thereto? And more than that, when they adviſed the ſame? If the ſecret Sacriledge of one <hi>Achan</hi> deſerved Gods indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt all his People of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> until they diſcovered, and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him, and his Offence? What doth the manifeſt extortion (a ſin no
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:111570:52"/>leſs prohibited than Sacriledge) of ſo many <hi>Achans,</hi> merit of Gods Judgements againſt the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>England,</hi> if they proſecute not, or leave unpuniſhed, their Offences, which are more than Extortions; as Perjuries, Forgeries, Sacriledge it ſelf, and divers others ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>Judge, O People? Judge, your ſelves, O ye People, leaſt ye be Judged.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF it pleaſe the Parliament to require more proofs than common experience of the common breach of all the Common Law of</hi> England, <hi>by our common Mercinary Judges, they may cauſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsions in</hi> Eyer, <hi>or other</hi> Oyers, <hi>and</hi> Terminers <hi>to be iſsued to clear the matter by more particular evidences.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:111570:53"/>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:111570:53"/>
                  <head>Eight Obſervable POINTS OF LAW; Executable by Juſtices of the Peace in their <hi>Counties,</hi> and Magiſtrates in their <hi>Corporations.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Neceſſary to be known to the COMMON PEOPLE.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> The choiſe of all Officers of Peace and Truſt, anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently in the People, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Magna Chart.</hi>
                     </note>1 <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ounties and She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs Turns, were ancient Courts in the time of King <hi>Arthur,</hi> &amp; before; And in the Turns were tried all Pleas of the Crown; &amp; in the Counties all <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fourty ſhillings without Writ; and above, to any value with Writs, according to the Law maxim, <hi>Quod placita de Catallis, debitis</hi> &amp;c. <hi>quae ſummam</hi> 40<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. <hi>attingunt, vel excedunt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:111570:54"/>ſecundùm legem &amp; conſuetudinem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, ſine brevi Regis placitari non debent.</hi> See the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> upon the 35<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chap. of <hi>Magna Charta;</hi> and upon the Stature of <hi>Glouceſter</hi> fol. 310. &amp; 312. Hundreds, and Court Burons have the ſame power, and rights, and neither Sheriffs nor Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are Judges, but ſuiters onely, fol. 312. And ſo all men were to have Law and Juſtice at home, cheap and near, and not to fetch it from <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> far and dear. And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervators, otherwiſe called Guardians of the Peace before <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> and ſince; had all neceſſary po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to govern their Counties in Peace, and to execute all Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing thereunto, and to command the power of their Counties to aſſiſt them; and were choſen (as all other Officers of Peace and Truſt were) by their Counties, as the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> This <hi>Mutuatus</hi> is uſual in the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> and <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> to fetch poor men not worth <hi>40. s.</hi> from <hi>York</hi> or <hi>Cornwall</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>5. s.</hi> debt or leſs; and to Outlaw him in the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> if he come not; which example other Courts of <hi>Record</hi> follow too much.</note>2. As Superiour Courts ought not to incroach upon Inferiour, ſo the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud the Superiour, of thoſe cauſes that belong
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:111570:54"/>to them: <hi>viz.</hi> Neither ought a man be ſued in any Court of <hi>Record</hi> for debt not amounting to 40<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. by way of <hi>mutuatus,</hi> and other lawleſs tricks dayly uſed by Attornies; nor in any inferiour Court for debt of 40 ſhillings, or exceeding, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding it into Actions under 40 ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. In which caſes the Defendant ought to be admitted to plead to the juriſdiction of the Court, and to have a <hi>Prohibition</hi> to ſtay the ſuit: ſee the Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> upon the Stat. of <hi>Glouc.</hi> fol. 311. And all Courts were to diſmiſs all Actions entred without ſufficient bail to proſecute, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for coſts and damages. If non-ſuited, or caſt; and not <hi>Jo. Do.</hi> and <hi>Rich. Ro.</hi> as is uſed. See <hi>F. H.</hi> Juſt. P. the Regiſter, and <hi>Fitz. H. Nat. brevium</hi> at large. And no Court of <hi>Record</hi> was to proceed in any action of debt, before the Plantiff ſwore his ſaid debt to be 40<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. or more, and his damage in treſpaſs to be ſo much at leaſt: And if Battery, that he was beaten indeed, to his uncurable hurt to that value. See the Stat. of <hi>Glouc.</hi> and the L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon it, with his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:111570:55"/>reaſon for the diſcontinuance of this practice.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>3.</hi> Doth not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of an <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> to bring a priſoner before a Judge without Fees, (both to Judge and Attorney) include the ſale, delay, and deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of Juſtice, while the priſoner is unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to buy it.</note>3. All the Kings Writs for the doing juſtice and right to all men freely and ſpeedily, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or denial, ought to be granted, and had freely at the Kings coſt: And juſtice ought to be done freely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſale; fully, without denial; and ſpeedily, without delay: whereby (ſaith the Lord <hi>Coke</hi>) it appeareth that juſtice muſt have three quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>viz.</hi> To be Free, becauſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more vile, than what is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; Full, and perfect, that it may not halt; And ſpeedy, becauſe delay is a kind of denial. See the L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon the Stat. of <hi>Marlbr.</hi> chap. 80. Thus to have and do, was the Common Law of <hi>England,</hi> and the Liberties, and Right of the <hi>People</hi> before <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and ſaved unto them by it: and the beſt Birth-right they ever had, or can have; whereby their Lands, Goods, Wives, Children, Bodies, Lives, Honours, and Eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ought to be protected from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries. See the L. <hi>C.</hi> upon the 29 &amp; 38 c. of <hi>M. C.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:111570:55"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>4.</hi> All defaults, &amp; offences of Sheriffs, Coroners Eſcheatours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> inquirable, and puniſhable by Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace.</note>4. Therefore <hi>Magna Char.</hi> ought to be read, and publiſhed to the People in all Cathedrals twice yearly: And all breakers thereof are excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> and ſo twice pronounced by two Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>Tit. confirm. &amp; excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mengm.t</hi> 
                     <hi>in Raſt. abridg.</hi> fol. 65. and 148. And it ought to be read in full County in every ſhire, four times yearly, and all the breakers thereof inquired of there; and further inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, and puniſhed by Fines, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by Juſtices in <hi>Eyre,</hi> two of every Counties chuſing, whereby 12. or 14. may ſerve in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits throughout <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> divided into ſix or ſeven Provinces, as twelve did ſerve for all <hi>England</hi> divided into ſix. See, and compare <hi>Raſt.</hi> abridg. fol. 65. and <hi>Rog. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veden parte poſter. Annal.</hi> fol. 548. The not reading, and publiſhing of <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> is the default partly of Sheriffs not requiring it; partly of the Clerk of the Crown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not ſending it to them under Seal. All defaults of Sheriffs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are inquira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and puniſhable by Juſtices of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:111570:56"/>Peace; as <hi>Lamb. Fitz. H. Cromp. Dali</hi> &amp;c. affirm at large.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>5.</hi> Obſerve the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples choice reſumed by this Statute, when the King preſumed to make Juſtices of P. and under that speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Title to impower them, firſt to affront, and by degrees to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, and at laſt to extinguiſh the larger power of Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. A Prerogative impoſture deviſed by Lawyers for their own advantage, when they got the King to confer this creation of Juſtices of Peace, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Chancellours, and Keepers, to whom their creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obliged to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject all <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Mag. Char.</hi>
                     </note>5. Juſtices in <hi>Eyre</hi> are diſcontinued long ſince, and not onely for that they were interrupted, and wearied out by the Prerogative Judges, and Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> by their <hi>Certioraries, Corpus cum cauſa, Errours,</hi> and other Writs (as the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> confeſſeth in his Expoſition of the Stat. called <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. ſuper Chart.</hi> fol. 540.) but alſo for that Juſtices of Aſſize, Juſtices of Peace, and all Oyers, and Terminers by their Commiſſions, and Magiſtrates of Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by their Charters, were enabled &amp; ſworn to hear and determine all Treſpaſſes, Contempts, Oppreſſions, and Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours, according to the Laws and cuſtoms of <hi>England,</hi> as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in, and by all Commiſſions of the Peace, Oyers, Terminers, and Charters that have Oyer and Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and by the Stat. made for the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:111570:56"/>firſt inſtitution of Juſtices of Peace, in the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> year of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. in which year was alſo ordained the Oath of all Judges, and Juſtices of Oyer and Terminer for the due execution of juſtice, without ſale, delay or denial, which the thrice reverend Judge <hi>Anthony Fitz Herb.</hi> admoniſheth them that conſider it, and their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God, and their Countrey, not to break upon any conditions, <hi>Nat. brevium</hi> fol. 240. d. but now the common practice is otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>6.</hi> Juſtices of Peace ought not to be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to tranſgreſs <hi>M. C.</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> by any Stat. that contradicts them, nor to loſe the publike intereſt for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prerogative uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, but to re-aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume their authority fro People, to act as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatours of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient peace, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: as in caſes of <hi>Remitter,</hi> men ſtand to their beſt Title.</note>6. Any that Will, ought to have Commiſſions of Oyer and Terminer for all Extortions, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Miſdemeanours of Sheriffs, Under ſheriffs, Eſcheatours, Bayliffs, Clerks, and all other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers: See <hi>Cromp.</hi> Juſt. Peace, fol. 51.8. <hi>Fitz H. Nat. br.</hi> fol. 112. d. And Juſtices of Peace, and all other Commiſſioners that ought by their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and Oaths, to puniſh all ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, &amp; do not, are no leſs than por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers, and the greateſt malefactours of all other, themſelves. Nor can any
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:111570:57"/>Writs of <hi>Certiorari, Corpus cum cauſa, Errour, Superſedeas,</hi> or putting out of Commiſſion, excuſe or ſupercede them to finiſh their Judgements, and Executions in all ſuch cauſes brought in queſtion before them: See and compare the Stat. of 2. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and 14. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.14. and the 20. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.1. and the <hi>Procedendo</hi> thereupon in <hi>Fitz. H. Na. Bre.</hi> fol. 240. where it is ſaid; <hi>They ſhall proceed to juſtice ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to law, notwithſtanding any Letter, Commandment, Prohibition, Writ, Privy-Seal, or Great Seal to the contrary.</hi> And if any ſuch things be granted by the King, or any of his Judges, or Coutrs, ſuch a <hi>Procedendo</hi> ought to be granted by the Keeper of the Broad Seal to countermand them; and to command juſtice, judgement, and execution to be done, even againſt the King, much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt Judges, who under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Authority and juſtice, delude and wrong Kings, and <hi>People: For</hi> (ſaith the L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon the Stat. of <hi>Marlebridge,</hi> cap. 5.) <hi>there is no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter injuſtice, than when under colour of Juſtice, men are injured:</hi> but <hi>Writs of Certiorari Corpus cum cauſa, and Errour,</hi> ought to be had, and granted,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:111570:57"/>upon proof of malice, partiality, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, or errour in matter, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any inferiour Court, but not upon ſuggeſtions, or bare ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as is uſed: See and compare therefore all the ſaid Statutes in this caſe, together with M. <hi>Dearhams</hi> Manuel, p. 25. Nor by any Superiour Judges or Courts that are parties, or concerned in the cauſe. See the L. <hi>Coke</hi> upon <hi>Art. ſuper Chart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>7.</hi> Theſe oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are daily commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by mercinary law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, by colour of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices againſt <hi>Mag. C.</hi> which Stat. ought to be repealed, &amp; the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er execution thereof reſiſted by all, or any neceſſary means.</note>7. The granting of Writs, or Commiſſions to do injuſtice by, or to ſtay, or delay juſtice, where it is done, or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or to deny Writs or Commiſſions to cauſe or further juſtice to be done, (which always was, and yet is the practice of the Prerogative Judges at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> not onely to croſs, &amp; interrupt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners legally choſen in, and by their Counties, (as Juſtices in Eyre were) and ſuch, and all Juſtices of Peace, and Officers of Truſt, and concernement in, and to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, ſtill ought to be) is the worſt of all Oppreſſions, and a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral deſtruction of Law and <hi>People,</hi>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:111570:58"/>committed by colour of an uſurped Authority, as ſaith the L. <hi>Coke</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Statute of <hi>Marlebr.</hi> cap. 5. To prevent which (his Lordſhip further ſaith) <hi>It is lawful for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to take up Arms, or for Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Judges to commit their Superiors and that before any Verdict, or Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe they worthily looſe the benefit of Law, who intend to ſubvert it; and Subordinate authority is more to be obeyed, and aſſiſted in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice, than the Supreameſt to be indured to obstruct it.</hi> All this, and more, is to be read in effect, in the L. <hi>Cokes</hi> Expoſition upon <hi>Art. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Char.</hi> and the Stat. of <hi>Marl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>br.</hi> which if executed by Juſtices of Peace in their Counties, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates in their Corporations, would ſoon regulate abuſes, ſettle Peace, and much inable the State, and Common-wealth to pay publike debts, and relieve diſtreſſed Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: For it is Law it ſelf, as virtue it ſelfe, invirtuateth, dignifieth, and authorizeth her true ſervants to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute her precepts; and confoundeth, expulſeth, and turneth out of her ſervice all her unjuſt Stewards, and underminers: As <hi>Jacob,</hi> and <hi>David</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:111570:58"/>were preferred before their elder brethren; and <hi>Saul, Jeroboam,</hi> &amp;c. were confounded by, and for their own Apoſtacies.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <note place="margin">As in all theſe caſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Peace ſhould be carefull to obſerve their Oaths, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form their duties to the Common-wealth (whereof they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent members) So, no doubt the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>England,</hi> would be ready to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt them in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ancient Birth-rights, Laws, and Liberties. <hi>Deus Faxit.</hi>
                     </note>8. Under the Titles of Treſpaſes, Contempts, Oppreſſions, Miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, are comprehended all breaches of <hi>Magna Char,</hi> and all Offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Statutes in force, and concurrent with <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> which all Juſtices of Peace, and Magiſtrates in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral juriſdictions, are Authorized, and ſworn to hear and determine, without fear, favour or reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. How then to be excuſed, or delayed by any Writ, or command of any Superiour? And how are the Judges of the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> (whereof the chief was the Kings Deputy by Writ) now Superiour, or equal to any other Judges, or Juſtices? If that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xim be true <hi>moritur Actio cum Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonâ?</hi> But the Office of a Deputy dyeth with its Maſter, as a Letter or Warrant of Attorney, with its ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker:
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:111570:59"/>the <hi>King-Bench</hi> may be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as well as his perſon? And all cauſes in this Common-wealth, be called Common-Pleas, and tryed by the Common Law of the land, and Verdicts of common people, and Free-holders of every County, and Corporation, before the Free Judges, &amp; Magiſtrates freely choſen by the ſaid Common and Free-Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to juſtifie them at home, and not before mercinary makers, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſellers of all Lawes, and Liberties, as they pleaſe at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> And doth not the ſaid Stat. of 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. warrant Juſtices of Peace, or any two of them (whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) to call and keep Seſſions as often as they ſee need to do juſtice to their Countrey? See the Stat. at large, and <hi>Cromp. I. P.</hi> fol. 112. and <hi>F. H. I. P.</hi> fol. 10.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto adde, That as <hi>Magna Charta</hi> compriſeth all the Law of this land agreed upon by Kings and People, and would be read and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Engliſh (as aforeſaid) for the better underſtanding thereof by all Engliſh People, to the end, that the ignorance of their Law, ſhould be not excuſe for any of them to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:111570:59"/>tranſgreſs it: So how needleſs it is, if not peſtiferous, to have this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Law reduced to a private mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinarie Trade, or particular ſcience exceeding the ſeven Liberal, by ſuch profeſſours thereof, as have, and do endeavour to diſguiſe, mask, and hide it from all but themſelves, in baſe French, and Latine intricacies and obſcurities, to the end to make all perſons offendors thereof, and none excuſable, but by their reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their own Riddles, which are alwaies anſwerable to their Fees (be the cauſe right or wrong) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the cure of Law becometh an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable diſeaſe, until that ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous mercinary profeſſion be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or regulated, ſo as the beſt and ſoundeſt Lawyers may be uſed in Parliaments (as in former times) to ſit upon Wol-ſacks, to anſwer to what that high Court ſhall be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to aske them, and not as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Court, to make Lawes, and Oaths for others, which they never obſerve themſelves but for their own gain, and the peoples da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: To which end, they alwaies preamble their inventions againſt <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> with titles of Acts for the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:111570:60"/>good of the people, when in their ſubſequents they hurt all but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; As (paſſing by all former) their laſt Acts for the inlarging of poor priſoners for debt, ſufficiently witneſs; whereby neither creditor nor debtour are any way relieved, but both further entangled, and Lawyers Fees more procreated; <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat experientia. Concluſivè;</hi> That there can be no firm peace, or end of Wars, till there be an end of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinarie profeſſours of Law, leſs needful, or uſeful for Parliaments or People, than Biſhops, or ſuch as might be uſed there, or elſwhere, for ſaying, or reading prayers; while theſe neither pray, preach, nor ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but their own lucrative magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence every where upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples purſes.</p>
                  <p>Adde laſtly; Such Juſtices of Peace as will not execute <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> with its confirmations, and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> and deſert, and wave the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and practice of contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Statutes, (for zeal to their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, or fear to be unmade by thoſe that made them) ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and waved by all good Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots of their countrey, as excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:111570:60"/>perſons, and breakers of <hi>M. Chà.</hi> And ſuch onely as will execute <hi>Mag. Ch.</hi> &amp;c. ought to be confirmed by the choiſe of the <hi>People</hi> in their Counties reſpectively, whereby they may act as the ancient Conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatours of the Peace did by the Common Law of <hi>England</hi> before <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and ſince, which was, to conſerve the Peace of <hi>England</hi> by all neceſſary means, word, or ſword; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited by Prerogative Statutes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by mercinary Lawyers, to ſteal from the People their birth-right Authority in the name of the King, unto themſelves, to ſell, delay, and deny it at their pleaſures; which to do, is apparently contrary, not onely to <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> and the Common Laws <hi>of England,</hi> and alſo to common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but chiefly to the divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God: for neither Law, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor Divine juſtice, would or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain a man to conſerve the publike peace of Gods people (which peace, as they, is his own) without giving that man an unlimitable power, by which he may execute his Office, and without which he cannot.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
